<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The spiritual house in its foundation, materials, officers, and discipline describ'd the nomothetical &amp; coercive power of the King in ecclesiastical affairs asserted the episcopal office and dignity, together with the liturgy of the Church of England vindicated in some sermons preached at St. Clement Danes and St. Gregories neer St. Pauls, London / by Geo. Masterson.</title>
            <author>Masterson, Geo. (George)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 173 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 68 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50109</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1073</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R30518</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11343343</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11343343</idno>
            <idno type="VID">47534</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50109)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 47534)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1466:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The spiritual house in its foundation, materials, officers, and discipline describ'd the nomothetical &amp; coercive power of the King in ecclesiastical affairs asserted the episcopal office and dignity, together with the liturgy of the Church of England vindicated in some sermons preached at St. Clement Danes and St. Gregories neer St. Pauls, London / by Geo. Masterson.</title>
                  <author>Masterson, Geo. (George)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 158 [i.e. 125] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Philemon Stephens the younger,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Numerous errors in pagination.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:47534:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:47534:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SPIRITUAL HOUSE In its Foundation, Materials, Officers, and Diſcipline DESCRIB'D. The Nomothetical &amp; Coercive Power of the KING, in Eccleſiaſtical Affaires ASSERTED. The Epiſcopal Office and Dignity, Together with the Liturgy of the Church of <hi>England</hi> VINDICATED.</p>
            <p>In ſome Sermons Preached at St. <hi>Clement Danes,</hi> and St. <hi>Gregories</hi> neer St. <hi>Pauls London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Geo. Masterſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Hath the Lord as great delight in Burnt Offerings and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, as in obeying the voice of the Lord? Behold, to obey is better then Sacrifice, and to hearken, then the fat of <hi>Rams,</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1</hi> Sam. <hi>15.22.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>And they anſwered <hi>Joſua,</hi> ſaying, All that thou commandeſt us wee will do, according as we hearkned unto <hi>Moſes</hi> in all things, ſo will we hearken unto thee,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Joſh. 1.16, 17.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certi Ap. Stobaeum.</p>
            <p>Printed for <hi>Philemon Stephens,</hi> the younger, living at the <hi>Golden Lyon</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls Church-Yard,</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:47534:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:47534:2"/>
            <head>To the great Exemplar of PIETIE &amp; VIRTUE, Frances, <hi>Dutches</hi> of <hi>Sommerſet</hi> Her Grace.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Gentile Superſtition, <hi>(Madam)</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd not the Names or their <hi>Deities</hi> upon the greateſt <hi>Donaries</hi> which they made
<pb facs="tcp:47534:3"/>them, with a Devotion comparable to that, with which I lay this <hi>Little Thing</hi> at Your Grace's Feet.</p>
            <p>The Compilement of this <hi>Structure</hi> is not in a Lofty and Noble <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thian</hi> form, with any Rich or Curious Embrodery of Words; but the whole is cemented together in the plain <hi>Tuſcan.</hi> I could have given it a Franker Light, had I not known that <hi>Devotion</hi> (for which
<pb facs="tcp:47534:3"/>this <hi>Spirituall Houſe</hi> was built) requires collected, rather then diffuſed Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits.</p>
            <p>I dare not aſſume the Vanity, to think that it is (as the <hi>Italians</hi> uſe to ſpeak of a well built Stru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture) <hi>Fabrica ben raccolta.</hi> But if Your Grace (who are ſo excellent a Judge) be pleas'd to afford it Your Approbation, for its uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs or ſeaſonableneſs, I ſhall rejoyce in my Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour: If otherwiſe, the
<pb facs="tcp:47534:4"/>hand that erected, ſhall be firſt upon it, to pull it in pieces, and condemn it to rubbage and ruine.</p>
            <p>But ſince <hi>(Madam)</hi> the ſimple Dedication of an Altar, (though the Mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials of it are but Turf or Brick, and the Hand that erected it, unacquainted with Art) hath ever ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd it againſt all, but Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegious Hands; I am ready to overcome my <hi>Reaſon</hi> into a <hi>Belief,</hi> that this (otherwiſe inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable)
<pb facs="tcp:47534:4"/>
               <hi>Piece,</hi> pleading the Cauſe of <hi>His moſt Sacred Majeſtie's</hi> Nomotheticall and Coercive Power in Matters of Religion, the Prelacy of my Lords, the Reverend Biſhops (as Governours ſent by him) and of the Pious (though deſpiſed) Liturgy of our Church (which three are fairly ſeated, and ruling in Your Graces Soul) it ſhall live under the ſhadow of Your great Name.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>(Madam)</hi> not
<pb facs="tcp:47534:5"/>without deep acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of Your Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces undeſerved Favours to my moſt unworthy Self, I take the boldneſs to aſſure you, that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining Thoughts and Actions of my Life, ſhall zealouſly aim at the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of being,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My moſt honoured Lady,</salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Graces moſt devoted Servant,</hi> Geo. Maſterſon.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Decemb. the</hi> 20th. 1660.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:47534:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1</hi> Epiſtle of <hi>Peter, 2</hi> Chap. <hi>4</hi> &amp; <hi>5</hi> verſ.</bibl>
                  <p>To whom coming as unto a living ſtone, diſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed indeed of Men, but choſen of God, and precious,</p>
                  <p>Ye alſo as lively ſtones, are built up a ſpirituall houſe, an holy prieſthood, to offer up ſpirituall ſacrifices acceptable to God, by Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE firſt thoughts that the Sons of Men entertain of coming (or drawing nigh) to God, are formed in them, by the mediation of his goodneſſe; that is, his profitableneſſe or ſerviceableneſſe to them, without this, all the beauty that is in the divine nature would never affect the heart of one of the lapſed Sons of <hi>Adam,</hi> for, though there be infinite charmes in the face of God, to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract the ſoules of all rationall Creatures that have eyes to behold the amiableneſſe that is in his face; yet the power and juſtice
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:47534:6"/>of God are more potent to deter the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, conſcious to it ſelf of its own unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe and guilt from coming to, or look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing toward him.</p>
            <p>The Son of God himſelf, though he be the brightneſſe of his Fathers glory, and the expreſſe image of his Perſon (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the character of his ſubſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence) would never lead one heart captive, were he not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> beneficient and grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, as well as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> anointed; ſo the Spouſe, Cantic. 1.3. <hi>Becauſe of the ſavour of thy good ointments, thy name is as ointment poured forth, therefore doe the Virgins love thee;</hi> and our Apoſtle (in my Text) menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons not their coming unto God, but upon the hypotheſis (or ſuppoſition) of their having <hi>taſted that the Lord is gracious, verſ.</hi> 3. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> his goodneſſe is the cords of a Man with which he drawes us, and we run after him; without a precedent taſt of that, we ſhould never come to him; But <hi>if ye have taſted,</hi> it neceſſarily and immediatly follows, <hi>To whom coming as unto a living ſtone, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which words, you have an alluſion to, or compariſon between the Chriſtian Church, and the Temple under the Law, (of which that was a type or figure) and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:47534:6"/>this alluſion ſtands in <hi>four</hi> things; the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, ſuperſtructure, prieſthood, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices.</p>
            <p n="1">1 You have here in anſwer to the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Temple, <hi>a ſtone;</hi> ſpecified, and illuſtrated by a peculiar Epithite <hi>[a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſtone]</hi> and deſcrib'd further by <hi>two</hi> things (for preventing that ſcandal (or of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence) that might be taken at it; becauſe <hi>diſallowed by men.</hi>) that men might not ſtumble at, or daſh their foot againſt this, it is true (ſaith our Apoſtle) this ſtone was <hi>diſallowed indeed of men;</hi> but firſt <hi>it was choſen of God;</hi> though it were reprobated by them, it was elected by him; <hi>non temere aſſumptus.</hi> And,</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>It is pretious too:</hi> 1 <hi>Coram Deo,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious in the ſight of God. 2 <hi>Apud fideles,</hi> precious in the eyes of all beleevers, who prefer this ſtone to all pearls and diamonds before the treaſures of ſilver and gold.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> You have here in alluſion to the Temple, the <hi>ſuperſtructure</hi> upon this foundation [ye alſo as lively ſtones are built up a <hi>ſpiritual houſe.</hi>]</p>
            <p n="3">3 The <hi>Prieſthood,</hi> dignified with the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable title of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> an <hi>holy prieſthood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The <hi>ſacrifices.</hi> 1 diſtinguiſhed from thoſe of the Law <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſpiritual,</hi> the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:47534:7"/>ſacrifices under the Law were <hi>carnal;</hi> but theſe are <hi>ſpiritual ſacrifiees.</hi> 2 The means how they become acceptable to God; namely by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 1. Alluſion is the foundation. <hi>[A ſtone]</hi> and heer 5. th: 1. that Chriſt is a ſtone. 2. How he is a ſtone. 3. How it fared with him (or what entertainment he found) he was <hi>diſallowed.</hi> 4. By whom. And <hi>5tly,</hi> their ſin in diſallowing him, in <hi>three</hi> reſpects. 1. Becauſe a <hi>living</hi> ſtone. 2. Becauſe <hi>choſen of God.</hi> And <hi>3dly</hi> becauſe <hi>precious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Chriſt is a ſtone; thus the holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets <hi>Iſaiah, Daniel,</hi> and <hi>Zachary</hi> prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied of him; Therefore thus ſaith the Lord God, behold I lay in <hi>Sion</hi> for a foundation, <hi>a ſtone, a tryed ſtone, a precious corner ſtone, a ſure foundation,</hi> Iſay. 28.16.</p>
            <p>Thou ſaweſt til that <hi>a ſtone was cut out without hands,</hi> which ſmote the Image, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.34. Behold the <hi>ſtone that I have laid before Joſhua: upon one ſtone ſhall be ſeven eyes, behold I will engrave the graving thereof ſaith the Lord of Hoſts,</hi> Zach. 3.9.</p>
            <p>Thus the holy Apoſtles Saint <hi>Peter</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> term him. <hi>This is the ſtone which was ſet at nought of you builders, which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the head of the corner, Acts</hi> 4.11. And did all drink of the ſame ſpiritual drink (for
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:47534:7"/>they drank of that ſpiritual rock that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed them) <hi>and that rock was Chriſt.</hi> 1 Cor. 10.4. He was a ſtone in his birth; <hi>Daniels</hi> ſtone, cut out of the mountain without hands; that is, made of a woman without a man. A ſtone in his paſſion: <hi>Zacharye's</hi> ſtone, graven and cut full of eyes. A ſtone in his reſurrection; <hi>Iſaiah's</hi> ſtone, layed in <hi>Sion</hi> for a foundation. A ſtone, of which the rock in the wilderneſſe was a type. now as that rock when it was ſmote by <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſent forth ſtreames of water for quenching the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> thirſt. So he, ſmitten in his paſſion, ſends forth baptiſmal water, to waſh us from our uncleanneſſe, and euchariſtical blood, to be our drink, to nouriſh us up unto eternal life. Thus Saint <hi>John</hi> tels you that our two Sacraments flowed from the ſide of our Saviour, when the Souldier peirced it with a ſpear. <hi>But one of the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers with a ſpear peirced his ſide, and forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with came there out blood and water,</hi> Joh. 19.34. Thus Chriſt as a <hi>ſtone</hi> (or rock) ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth ſtreames, beſpeaks the Jewes. In the laſt day, that great day of the feaſt, <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> ſtood, and cryed ſaying, <hi>if any man thirſt let him come unto me and drink.</hi> John. 7.37. Thus he ſaith likewiſe of the ſtreames of his grace. <hi>Whoſoever drinketh of the water that I
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:47534:8"/>ſhall give him, ſhall never thirſt; but the water that I ſhall give him, ſhall be in him a well of water, ſpringing up into everlaſting life.</hi> Joh. 4.14. Thus he is a ſtone, a ſtone ſending forth ſtreams of living water.</p>
            <p n="2">2 How is Chriſt a ſtone; He is a ſtone, (that is, metaphorically, or in an allegory as a ſtone) in a threefold reſpect.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 In reſpect of his humane nature; he was hewen out of the ſame rock, dig'd out of the ſame quarry, as the reſt of the Sons of men are; he was a ſtone <hi>of the old rock</hi> Adam, he was dig'd out of <hi>Abrahams</hi> quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, made of a woman; he took part of the ſame fleſh and blood that the other chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren doe; he was like unto us in all things <hi>ſin only excepted;</hi> he was of the ſame rock with us, <hi>only without any, the leaſt flaw.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 In reſpect of his paſſion; Nothing is more ſubject to contempt to be trod upon, to be ſpurn'd out of the way then a ſtone; The Kingly Prophet (ſpeaking in the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Chriſt) ſaith, <hi>I am a worm and no man,</hi> Pſal. 22.6. He might have ſaid <hi>lapis ac non vir,</hi> a ſtone and no man; a contemptible ſtone in his paſſion, rather then a man; never were any ſufferings like his ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, never any ſorrows like his ſorrows; and yet behold, never was any Perſon in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:47534:8"/>the midſt of his ſorrows and ſufferings, ſo patient, ſo ſtil, ſo ſtone like; <hi>He was op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, and he was afflicted, yet he opened not his mouth.</hi> Iſaiah. 53.7.</item>
               <item>3 In reſpect of his ſtrength and ſolidity; The chief virtue and propertity of a ſtone is, that it is firm and ſure; Hence it is, that men place it in the foundation, and venture the fabrick upon it. Chriſt is a ſtone in this reſpect eſpecially; ye may truſt him, ye may confidently build upon him, ye may ſafely venture all your temporal and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal concernments upon this foundation; he is the true rock, upon which whoſoever builds his houſe ſhall ſtand, <hi>though the rain deſcend, and the floods come, and the windes blow and beat upon it.</hi> It is the ſtrength, ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility and ſolidity of Chriſt eſpecially, that gives him the denomination of a ſtone heer; as in the verſe immediately following the Text; Wherefore it is contained in the Scripture, behold I lay in <hi>Sion</hi> a chief cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſtone, &amp;c. <hi>And he that beleeveth on him ſhall not be confounded.</hi> 1 Pet. 2.6.</item>
            </list>
            <p>As the gates of Hell cannot prevail a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Church, <hi>becauſe it is founded upon a Rock, Math.</hi> 16.18. no more ſhall the gates of Hell prevail againſt the particuler ſoule, that is <hi>regularly</hi> built upon this ſtone,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:47534:9"/>this ſolid and ſure foundation; and thus you have an account of the ſecond thing, how Chriſt is a ſtone: come we now to ſee what entertainment he finds, how it fared with him, which is the third thing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The entertainment of this ſtone. The Text tels you <hi>he was diſſallowed,</hi> the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh expreſſion (in our tranſlation) is too modeſt. It is in the language that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle wrote <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>reprobatus</hi> (Beza) <hi>reprobaverunt (Trem.)</hi> it was not a bare ſimple <hi>diſſallowing</hi> but a down right <hi>reprobating</hi> of him, and this they did two wayes.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. In their words; when they ſtiled him <hi>a deceiver: That deceiver,</hi> with an empha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis, Sir we remember (ſay the Chief Prieſts and Phariſes unto <hi>Pilat</hi>) <hi>that, that deceiver ſaid.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.63. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> as if he had been the greateſt Impoſtor, the verieſt cheat, that ever was in the World. <hi>A man gluttonous and a wine bibber, a friend of publicans and ſinners,</hi> Mat. 11.19. <hi>A Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritan and one that had a Devill,</hi> Joh. 8.48. <hi>Belzebub the God of flies or prince of Devils,</hi> Mat. 12.24. did they not reprobate him when they ſaid <hi>we will not have this man to rule over us? Luke</hi> 19.14. if this may be
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:47534:9"/>conſtrued but a diſſallowing of him, that (I am ſure) was an avowd <hi>reprobation,</hi> when they put the higheſt indignity upon him, in preferring <hi>Barrabbas</hi> before him, <hi>John</hi> 18. <hi>ult.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. They reprobated him by their works, you have ſeen the generation among whom our Lord Chriſt lived, with whom he cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers'd in the daies of his fleſh, laying him aſide as a contemptible, refuſe ſtone, to which they would not afford any room or place in the building: you may behold them now actually reprobating him, in their ſcourging of him, crowning him with thorns, nayling him to the Croſſe, and piercing his ſide. He was not onely <hi>a man of ſorrows &amp; acquainted with grief</hi> (as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Iſay c.</hi> 53. <hi>verſ.</hi> 3.) but (as the ſame Prophet <hi>verſ.</hi> 5.) <hi>He was wounded for our tranſgreſſions, he was bruiſed for our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties:</hi> had he been a caſt-away, a perſon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probated of God, they could not have treated him worſe then they did, when he thirſted, thyy gave him Vinegar to drink: they powered upon him the utmoſt that ſpite and malice could invent when the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry pangs of death were upon him, they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted upon him a ſhamefull, painfull, cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed death, they crucified him, and they
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:47534:10"/>crucified him between two thieves, as the greateſt and chiefeſt malefactor.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Apoſtle ſaith of him (in a patheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal admiration of his humiliation) that he humbled himſelfe, and became obedient unto death, even the death of the Croſs: it may be truly ſaid of thoſe with whom he convers'd <hi>reprobaverunt ad mortem mortem autem crucis</hi> they rejected him to death, the death of reprobates, the death that hath a curſe annexed to it, the death of the Croſs, they proſecuted him in their rage and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, till they brought him <hi>lapis ad lapidem,</hi> into a grave of ſtone, and then rolled a ſtone upon him, and ſo left him diſſallowed (or reprobated) with a witneſſe.</p>
            <p>But if he were a ſtone; that is incapable of diſgrace, utterly unacquainted with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, it is neither ſenſible of what is ſpoke, nor of what is done to it, the tongue that caſts it aſide with reproach, the hand that cuts and hews it, doth it not affect it any thing at all.</p>
            <p>It is true, a ſtone indeed is inſenſible, but Chriſt was <hi>a living ſtone</hi> a ſtone endud with life and ſenſe, a perſon very tender and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of the wounds they gave him with their tongues, the reproaches, taunts, and ſcofs, they caſt upon him, and of thoſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:47534:10"/>likewiſe ef their hands, he was ſenſible of the furrows which they made upon his back, the whips, the thornes, the nayles and ſpear, he was ſenſible of them all, he endured all patiently as a ſtone, but he felt it ſenſibly as a living ſtone. witneſſe two things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. His paſſionate prayer, <hi>Father if it be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible let this cup paſſe from me,</hi> the cup of his paſſion, it was the cup of red wine, the cup of his Fathers diſpleaſure: and this pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er he repeats no leſſe then three times, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.44.</item>
               <item>2, The apprehenſion he had of his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing ſufferings, which was ſo great that it caſt him into that agony, in which he ſweat drops of blood, <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.44. whereby he made good this compellation of a ſtone, which uſe to give or ſweat againſt rain or ſtorms. he could not but be ſenſible of the Tempeſt when it fell upon him, who thus ſwet in the ſenſe of it before it came. and thus you ſee (the third thing) what enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment he found, he was diſſallowed or reprobated.</item>
            </list>
            <p>But by whom was he thus dealt with? That is the,</p>
            <p n="4">4. Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith (in the Text) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>(of men)</hi> of mean men it may
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:47534:11"/>be, the multitude who know not the worth or valew of a ſtone. Nay, but they were <hi>the builders,</hi> they who ſhould know what ſtone is fit for every place: ſo our Lord Chriſt, Did you never reade in the Scriptures, the ſtone <hi>which the builders re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected,</hi> the ſame is become the head of the corner? <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.42. and ſo Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> This is the ſtone which was ſet at nought <hi>of you builders, Acts</hi> 4.11. and the builders generally, univerſally; have <hi>any</hi> of the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers or of the Phariſes believed on him, <hi>John</hi> 7.48. He among them who thought ſo well of himſelfe as a chief maſter buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that he deſpiſed the reſt as perſons who knew nothing, <hi>Caiaphas,</hi> was poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, and abſolutely for the reprobating of him. <hi>One of them named</hi> Caiaphas <hi>being the highprieſt that ſame year, ſaid unto them, ye know nothing at all, nor conſider that it is expedient for us, that one man</hi> (meaning Chriſt) <hi>ſhould die for the people, John</hi> 11.49, 50. Now lay theſe together, and you have a ſad account of the lot that befell Chriſt, he was refuſed, (or diſſallowed) refuſed by the builders, by the chiefe of them, yea he was not onely diſſallowed, that is, not afforded to be the head, but he was reprobated, not allowed any room
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:47534:11"/>in the building; to be refuſed is not ſo much, it may be more honour (as the Tryers may prove) to be rejected, then approved by them; but to be refuſed of builders, who are preſum'd to be skilfull, and by the chiefe of them, this is much indeed.</p>
            <p>Againe, to be diſſallowed, not admitted to the chief place, this is not ſo much, for there are other places in the building in which he might have been ſet with ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, but to be wholly and abſolutely reprobated, not allowed any place but to be caſt out among the rubbiſh, this is hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be under gone, and yet this was the lot of Chriſt, he was diſſallowed not by menſimply, but by the builders, the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſedly wiſeſt men. and that leads me to the</p>
            <p n="5">5. Particuler, the aggration of their ſin in diſſallowing him.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Becauſe he was <hi>a living ſtone,</hi> who hath life in himſelfe, even as the Father hath life in himſelfe. <hi>As the Father hath life in himſelfe, ſo hath he given to the Son to bave life in himſelfe, John</hi> 5.26. a living ſtone, who gives life to all others, all kinds of life, temporall, ſpirituall, eternall, the life of nature, grace and glory. <hi>In him was life,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:47534:12"/>John</hi> 1.4. not in the <hi>Scocinians</hi> ſenſe, <hi>Quia Chriſtus primus vitam aeternam &amp; caeleſtem an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciavit, &amp; revelavit, (Smalcius.)</hi> becauſe he firſt preached eternall life. or life <hi>per meto nimiam pro vitae aeternae clariſſimo nuntio (Schlichtingius.)</hi> the moſt eminent Preacher of life; but the meaning of the Text <hi>in him was life</hi> is originally radically as in the head or heart, from whence it is commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated to all the members; ſo that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting, diſallowing, or refuſing of this li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſtone, is (being interpreted) the refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of life it ſelfe, the chooſing of death rather then life.</item>
               <item>2. Becauſe he was <hi>choſen of God,</hi> the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probating of that which God hath elected, is an high aggravation of ſin: becauſe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the fooliſhneſſe of man exalts it ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the wiſedom of the onely wiſe God. Had Chriſt been a ſtone accidentally or by chance aſſum'd by men, had he been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded for the advancement or carrying on of ſome politick deſigne, he might have been diſallowed without any eminent ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard: but when God in infinite wiſedome, and upon mature deliberation hath made choice of him, as the only proper founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of mans happineſſe, he cannot be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probated by any, without adding many
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:47534:12"/>cubits to the ſtature of their tranſgreſſion.</item>
               <item>3. Becauſe <hi>he is precious,</hi> that is truly and properly precious, <hi>cujus exiguum alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius magnum exaequat,</hi> a little of which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſats a great deal in other maters, Chriſt is the pearl of price which the wiſe Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantman ſels all that he hath to purchaſe, Chriſt is ſo precious that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted his greateſt priviledges, his choiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſervices yea and all things but loſſe and dung in compariſon of him <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.5, 6, 7, 8. to reject therefore a thing or perſon ſo precious as Chriſt is, is an exceeding high aggravation of their ſin, he was <hi>a living ſtone, choſen of God and precious</hi> and yet <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allowed of men.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Lay Chriſt then (to improve this firſt general in a few words) the foundation of your happineſſe, as he was deſign'd by the God of Heaven; the Apoſtle tels you in the 1. to the Corinth. 3. chap. &amp; 11 verſ. <hi>Other foundation can no man lay, then that is layed, which is Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> This is the rock upon which the wiſe builder erects his fabrick; all others are but ſandy foundations; the Houſe that is built upon them, the expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that men raiſe from them, muſt fall in the day of the rain or tempeſt. As for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</p>
            <list>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:47534:13"/>
               <item>1 They who build upon the bare name of Chriſtianity. There is a vaſt difference between nominals and reals; names will never paſſe in the account of Heaven for things. The Church of <hi>Sardis</hi> had a faire name <hi>[a name that ſhe lived]</hi> but this did not advantage her any thing, becauſe <hi>[ſhe was dead] Apoc.</hi> 3.1.</item>
               <item>2 They who build upon the ſhoulders of their religious progenitors, <hi>the Grand-Mother Lois, and the Mother Evnice.</hi> It is an happineſſe too great for Parents to entail their graces together with their eſtates up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their children; all the holineſſe they derive to them, is a faederal holineſſe only; a leprous Father begets a leprous child; the Father takes a potion, and is healed of his leproſy, but if the child uſe not that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, he dies in his uncleanneſſe; if you reflect upon the children of many holy men in Scripture, you may behold <hi>Adams Cain, Abrahams Iſmael, Iſaacks Eſau, Davids Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non</hi> &amp; <hi>Abſolom, Aarons Nadab</hi> &amp; <hi>Abihu, Elies Hophni</hi> &amp; <hi>Phineas:</hi> too many chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are like Manaſſes;
<q>
                     <l>Hoc uno patris ſpectaculum</l>
                     <l>Quod ejus imaginem reddidi ex contrario.</l>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>(Eman. Theſaur.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </item>
               <item>3 They who expect the end without
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:47534:13"/>the means; who build upon their predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. There is a predeſtination to works as well as to life. For we are his workman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip created in Chriſt Jeſus unto good works, <hi>which God hath before ordained that we ſhould walk in them,</hi> Epheſ. 2.10.</item>
               <item>4 They who rely upon poor, weak, lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing intentions, that never ripen into action; the Poet derides thoſe whoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions were alwayes bloſſoming, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver brought forth any ripe fruit, <hi>cras te victorum, &amp;c.</hi> good intentions fortifyed, with pious reſolutions doe fairly introduce one into the paths of virtue, but the beſt intentions without action will never bring him to his journeys end. The Jewes (I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve) intended as they ſaid, when they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired the Prophet to pray for them, and (ſay they) <hi>according to all that the Lord our God ſhall ſay, ſo declare unto us, and we will doe it,</hi> Jeremiah 42.20. and yet he tels them they diſſembled in their hearts, when they ſent him unto the Lord; becauſe (ſaith he) <hi>I have declared it to you, but ye have not obeyed the voyce of the Lord, nor any thing for which he hath ſent me unto you,</hi> verſ. 21. good intentions are like the Angel that went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Toby</hi> to <hi>Rages;</hi> but the non execuion of them, is like the dog that followed after him.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:47534:14"/>
5 They who build upon their civil ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, or negative goodneſſe; they doe no man wrong; they are not this or that; the Scribes and Phariſes, were (without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy) unblameable in their converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on towards men; and it is not to be queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd but that the Phariſe ſpake truth, who ſaid <hi>God I thank thee, that I am not as other men are, extortioners, unjuſt, adulterers, I faſt twice in the weeke, I give tithes of all that I poſſeſſe,</hi> Luke 18.11, 12. and yet our Lord Chriſt ſaith, except your righteouſneſſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the righteouſneſſe of the Scribes and Phariſes, ye ſhall in no caſe enter into the Kingdom of heaven, <hi>Mat</hi> 5.20.</item>
               <item>6 They who build upon their religious performances, their own righteouſneſſe; Chriſt became a ſtone of offence to the Jews, when they would be ſaved by the works of the Law. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.31, 32. and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Chriſt is become of none effect unto you, whoſoever of you, are juſtified by the Law; ye are fallen from grace.</hi> Galat. 5.4.</item>
            </list>
            <p>We may ſafely ſay of all theſe, as Chriſt did to his Diſciples (when they ſhew'd him the fabrick of the material Temple) <hi>there ſhall not be left one ſtone upon another, that ſhall not be throwen down.</hi> Mark. 13.2.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Take heed of diſalowing or rejecting Chriſt. <hi>Beza</hi> (upon the T.) ſaith <hi>etiam nos
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:47534:14"/>hodie vita &amp; moribus reprobamus.</hi> Men may, and doe at this day reject Chriſt by their vitious lives, and evil manners; they reject or reprobate him in general who are diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient to the word. <hi>A ſtone of ſtumbling and a rock of offence, even to them which ſtumble at the word, being diſobedient.</hi> 1 Pet. 2.8. they more particularly, who refuſe, neglect or deſpiſe his ordinances; the rejecting of them, is the rejecting of Chriſt in his wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and faithfulneſſe.</p>
            <p>Every man that lives in a known ſin, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers <hi>Barabbas</hi> before him.</p>
            <p>It is this, and this only, that renders it a thing perfectly reaſonable that the ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of ſinners ſhould be eternal, in the place of torment, becauſe by rejecting Chriſt, they contemn that immortal and eternal life, which God puts into their hands, and upon which they might lay hold, by em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing and entertaining him. Is there any thing more rational and equal then this, that when God ſets life and death before men, immortal life by entertaining Chriſt, and eternal death by rejecting him, they who chooſe death, ſhould have their portion or part in it? Take heed leaſt while you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge (as you cannot but doe) the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonableneſſe of this, you doe not (as the Jews did) condemn your ſelves in a <hi>thir d</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:47534:15"/>Perſon. <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.41. and ſo I paſſe from this to the ſecond general.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The ſuperſtructure or fabrick, that is built upon this foundation. <hi>ye alſo as lively ſtones are built up a ſpiritual houſe, verſ.</hi> 5. In which there are three things conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; the materials, edifice, and the manner how it becometh ſuch.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The materials are 1. in general <hi>[ye]</hi> 2. more particularly <hi>[lively ſtones]</hi> If you would know,</p>
            <p n="1">1 Who theſe <hi>[ye]</hi> are, you muſt have recourſe to the beginning of this Epiſtle; in the firſt and ſecond verſes of the firſt chapter, they are deſcrib'd by two names, <hi>ſtrangers</hi> and <hi>elect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Strangers: advenis, inquilinis; in ſolos Judaeos competit.</hi> It appertaines to the Jews only (ſaith Maſter <hi>Calvin</hi> upon the place) who are here called <hi>ſtrangers,</hi> not as the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers are afterwards, <hi>I beſeech you as ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and pilgrims abſtain from fleſhly luſts,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.11. becauſe heaven is their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and they are heer from home; but becauſe they were caſt out from that Land (the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi>) which was peculier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly theirs; and were now diſpers'd and ſcattered through <hi>Pontus, Galatia, Cappa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>docia, &amp;c.</hi> Or,</p>
            <p>Advenis, <hi>ſtrangers;</hi> i. e. <hi>ijs qui ex genti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſmo
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:47534:15"/>in rem publicam populi Dei tranſierant. (Gualt.)</hi> who were tranſplanted from gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiliſme into the Society of Gods people. I undertake not to umpire between <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Gualter</hi> whether they were Jews or Gentiles; but take that which they both agree in, the <hi>[ye]</hi> heer, the materials of this ſpiritual houſe to be Chriſtians; that is, perſons made proſelites to the faith and profeſſion of Chriſt, whether from the tents of Judaiſme or gentiliſme, it matters not. the <hi>[ye]</hi> are Chriſtians, they the materials of this ſpiritual houſe; but not all we hope <hi>(will ſome ſay)</hi> for the Apoſtle ſtiles them.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Elect.</hi> whence they infer, that none ought to be accounted members of the Church, (the materials of this ſpiritual houſe) but the <hi>elect</hi> only.</p>
            <p>The <hi>elect</hi> in their ſenſe, are (I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg) the ſole Members of the inviſible Church, but all that profeſſe the name of Chriſt, may, and ought to be reputed mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the viſible Church. This Saint <hi>Paul</hi> hath put wholy out of controverſy by tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling us, that <hi>in a great houſe, there are, not only veſſels of gold and of ſilver, but alſo of wood, and of earth: and ſome to honor, and ſome to diſhonor,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.20.</p>
            <p>And for the <hi>elect</hi> (in Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Text) the great Patrons of abſolute and irreſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:47534:16"/>election, underſtand them either of general election to Chriſtianity: <hi>electis</hi> i. e. <hi>defaece hominum ſegregatis, ad meliorem quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam ſortem.</hi> (Aret.) <hi>elect.</hi> that is ſeparated from the dregs and vap of mankind, to a better lot and portion in Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>Or (at moſt) elect in the judgment of charity, ſo <hi>Calvin,</hi> Gods election being a ſecret laid up in his own boſom, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be known but by the ſinguler and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial revelation of the holy ghoſt <hi>quaeri poteſt unde hoc compertum habuerit.</hi> It may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded how the Apoſtle knew that theſe Perſons were elect? and his anſwer is, we may not anxiouſly enquire concerning the election of our Brethren, but make our judgment of it from their vocation, <hi>ut pro electis habeantur, quicunque per fidem, in ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam ſunt coaptati:</hi> that they ſhould be deem'd elect who are joyned unto the Church by faith: <hi>eſt enim hoc charitatis, non fidei judicium;</hi> the utmoſt judgment that we can make in this caſe being of charity only, and not aſſurance: and he ſums up his reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution in theſe words, <hi>quatenus ergo prae ſe ferebant ſe Dei ſpiritu regenitos, in electis Dei ipſos numerat.</hi> For as much therefore as they profes'd themſelves regenerate by the holy ghoſt, he reckons them among the elect. This ſecond title then <hi>elect</hi> doth not <hi>(even
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:47534:16"/>in the judgment of theſe men)</hi> oppoſe or gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay our interpretation of [ye] by Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, all that profeſſe the faith of Chriſt. And thus you ſee in general who are the materials of this houſe [ye] Chriſtians.</p>
            <p n="2">2 More particulerly <hi>lively</hi> (or living ſtones) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Chriſtians are here called <hi>living ſtones</hi> (waving ſome other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects) by way of antitheſis (or oppoſition) eſpecially, to thoſe inanimate (or dead) ſtones, that were the materials of the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Temple. <hi>Living ſtones,</hi> i. e. ſuch as have a principle of life and motion in themſelves. And they are therfore ſaid in the preceding verſe to come unto the foundation. (to whom coming.)</p>
            <p>The ſtones in the material Temple were not active (they did not offer themſelves, or come unto the foundation.) but meerly paſſive, they were brought and layed upon it; but heer the ſtones are active, and come; and accordingly the Apoſtle beſpeaks them <hi>as living ſtones</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> not only <hi>aedifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cati</hi> (as <hi>Beza</hi>) whom our tranſlation fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows) <hi>built;</hi> but <hi>aedifice mini</hi> (as <hi>Tremel.</hi> and the Margin in our Bibles,) <hi>be ye bvilt;</hi> which cleerly implies not a little activity in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, in building up themſelves.</p>
            <p>No doctrine hath ever ſhed a more ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant influence upon religion, or caſt the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:47534:17"/>Profeſſors of it, into ſo deep a ſleep, as that which with an open face and directly, or by conſequence and with a glance of its eye, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribes the whole work of our ſalvation ſo to God, as to deny man any activity in the conduct or promoting of it. For, they who are excited with the greateſt earneſtneſſe to build up themſelves, are yet too prone to lye ſtill in the duſt, but when men perſwade themſelves, (or are taught by others to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve) that they cannot contribute any thing towards the building up of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, they muſt unavoidably remain rivet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to, or rooted in the earth, without any endeavour of coming to the foundation, making any application of themſelves to Chriſt. As <hi>Suetonius</hi> obſerves of <hi>Tiberius, religionum negligentiorem fuiſſe, guippe perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionis plenum cuncta fato agi;</hi> he was the more careleſſe in the things of religion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was full of this perſwaſion, that all things are guided by fate; to prevent this the Apoſtle tels Chriſtians, that they are <hi>living ſtones;</hi> in which expreſſion as the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges of Chriſtians are couch'd, ſo their duty is implyed; for as <hi>living ſtones</hi> you have a principle of reaſon and underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to judge of the foundation, whether it be a rock or ſand; as <hi>living ſtones</hi> you are endued with wils, to make choice of the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:47534:17"/>rock or ſands, as your foundation, to come, or not to come to, to build, or not to build upon the living ſtone, Chriſt. And thus you have an account of the 1. particuler the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terials of this houſe [ye] and ye as <hi>living ſtones.</hi> the next thing to be conſidered, is,</p>
            <p n="2">The aedifice, <hi>a ſpiritual houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>An Houſe.</hi> Thus the Church is fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ſtiled in Scripture: <hi>that thou mayeſt know how thou oughteſt to behave thy ſelfe in the houſe of God, which is the Church of the living God,</hi> 1 Tim. 3.15. &amp; Heb. 3.5, 6. <hi>and Maſes verily was faithfull in all his houſe as a Servant, but Chriſt as a Son over his own houſe, whoſe houſe are we, &amp;c.</hi> the Church is caled <hi>an houſe,</hi> either metonymically, as the houſe is put for the family that inhabit it. as Gen. 7.1. <hi>and the Lord ſaid unto Noah, come thou and all thy houſe into the Ark. And now</hi> (ſaid Jacob, Gen 30.30.) <hi>when ſhall I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for mine own houſe alſo?</hi> or <hi>an houſe</hi> by way of alluſion principally to the Temple, or unto any other houſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>A ſpirituall houſe.</hi> That is, metapho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rically, and alluſively, to all intents and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes in ſpiritual things, that which an houſe is in temporal. The eſtate of Chriſtians (as they are in Society) is ſet forth to us in Scripture, in divers and ſundry terms; ſometimes of a flock, <hi>ye are his flock</hi> fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:47534:18"/>in the Pſalms; ſometimes of huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry, <hi>ye are Gods husbandry,</hi> 1 Cor. 3.9. ſometimes of a building, <hi>ye are Gods build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> 1 Cor. 3.9. and ſo in the Text, <hi>a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this <hi>ſpiritual houſe</hi> (without offering violence to the allegory) there are (as in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very wel built material houſe) 3. things e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially requiſit; ſymetry, decor, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribution.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Symetry,</hi> This in a material building is the convenience or proportion that run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth between the parts and the whole; and this reconciles thoſe ſeemingly oppoſite things, <hi>uniformity</hi> and <hi>variety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> is ſo neceſſary (if not to the beeing, yet) to the well or comely beeing of any houſe, that without this, it is but a confuſed heap; yet it is not to be imagined that the moſt uniform building ſhould not admit of variety; for, Art muſt be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged in its higheſt pefection, when it may be reduc'd to ſome natural principle. (the moſt judicious Artiſts being but the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miques of nature.)</p>
            <p>Now the natural fabrick of Mans body is (according to the ſaying of <hi>Protagoras</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the proto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>type of all exact ſymetry; no ſtructure can be (poſſibly) more uniform then our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:47534:18"/>in the whole figuration of them, each ſide agreeing with the other, both in the number, the quality, and in the meaſure of the parts: and yet there is great variety and diverſity; for, ſome are round as the armes, other flat as the hands; ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent, and ſome more retired; thus in the <hi>ſpiritual houſe</hi> (the Church) though there be great <hi>variety:</hi> ſome learned, other un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned; ſome rich, other poor, ſome noble and honourable, other mean and vile; ſome ſtrong men, other babes in Chriſt; ſome Fathers, other children.</p>
            <p>Or as, though in an houſe there be a cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, pantry, kitchin, and other rooms of meaner office, as well as a parlour, bed-chamber, and cloſet: and great variety be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween theſe in reſpect of form, height and latitude; yet becauſe there is a convenience and proportion running between the parts and the whole; this ſatisfies for the diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, and reconciles it (by the force of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion) to that regularity or ſymetry that ought to be in the building, So in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual houſe (the Church) though the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers be various, yet they may be correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondent, if the conveniency or proportion (in which ſymetry conſiſts) be held: and it muſt neceſſarily be with that Church, in which this ſymetry is found, as they ſay of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:47534:19"/>the material Church of <hi>Santa Giuſtina</hi> in <hi>Padova</hi> (though the materials be but ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtone, without any garniſhment of ſculp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) yet <hi>it raviſheth the beholders eye, by a ſecret harmony in the proportion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Decor. This (in a material houſe) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in the keeping of a due reſpect between <hi>the habitation</hi> and the <hi>Inhabitant.</hi> It was the ſaying of a great Artiſt (<hi>Palladius</hi>) that no fabrick is to be regulated by any certain di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſions, but by the dignity only of the Maſter. The Gentiles having reſpect to this were profuſely liberal in adorning their Temples (witneſſe that of <hi>Ceres Eleuſina</hi> at <hi>Epheſus</hi>) upon perſwaſion that their Gods dwelt in them: and the God of heaven (though he doe not dwel in Temples made with hands as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> tels the Men of <hi>Athens,</hi> Acts 17.24.) yet (becauſe the Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was dedicated to his worſhip, and appropriated to him) he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains (by the Prophet <hi>Haggai</hi>) for want of this <hi>decor,</hi> the not keeping a due reſpect be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the habitation and himſelf the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitant. <hi>Is it time for you, oh ye, to dwell in your cealed houſes, and this houſe lye waſt?</hi> Hag. 1.4. In the ſpiritual houſe, (the Church) in which God hath ſaid he will dwell for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, the decor is <hi>holineſſe:</hi> the Inhabitant is holy, and therefore the habitation ſhould be ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:47534:19"/>
It is true of the ſpiritual houſe, that <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> ſpeaks of the material Temple, <hi>Holineſs becometh thine honſe oh Lord for ever,</hi> Pſal. 93. and upon the account of his own holineſſe, God requires this due reſpect. <hi>It is written be ye holy, for I am holy.</hi> 1 Pet. 1.16. and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> urgeth it likewiſe upon the ſame account. <hi>Know ye not that ye are the Temple of God, and that the ſpirit of God dwelleth in you? if any Man defile the Temple of God, him ſhall God deſtroy: for the Temple of God is holy, which Temple ye are.</hi> 1 Cor. 3.16, 17.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Diſtribution. The deſigning of all the rooms to their ſeveral and reſpective offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. In the ſpiritual houſe likewiſe, there muſt be ſuch a diſtribution. Thus the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>and he gave ſome Apoſtles, and ſome Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and ſome Evangeliſts, and ſome Paſtors, and Teachers.</hi> Epheſ. 4.11. and more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, 1 Cor. 12.28. <hi>God hath ſet ſome in the Church, firſt Apoſtles, ſecondarily Prophets, thirdly Teachers, &amp;c.</hi> for as (in material buildings) ſome ſtones doe well within dores, that would not ſerve without, to bear out weather: and others doe better without then they would doe within: ſo ſome Chriſtians are more for uſe, and leſſe for ornament; others more for ornament and leſſe for uſe: as therefore God (in his wiſedome) hath deſign'd and appointed
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:47534:20"/>men, ſo they ought to keep their ſtation, to continue in that calling or place which ye Mr. <hi>Builder</hi> hath diſtributed to them: and thus you have an account of the 2d. thing; the ſuperſtructure a <hi>ſpiritual houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 The manner how Chriſtians become ſuch an houſe: and that is, <hi>by being built up or building up themſelves:</hi> ſo (if this Text doe not beare it) Saint <hi>Jude</hi> ſaith expreſly <hi>But ye beloved, building up your ſelves on your moſt holy faith,</hi> verſ. 20. for (though it be ſtrange, yet) it is true, we are both <hi>ſtones,</hi> and <hi>builders:</hi> to be built, and to build up our ſelves. <hi>Stones,</hi> in reſpect of them whom God hath ſet over us, to ſquare and frame us; and <hi>builders</hi> in reſpect of our ſelves firſt, and then of thoſe who are committed to us, either by the obligation of ditty or cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; every one being to build up thoſe that are committed to his charge, into an houſe for God to dwell in.</p>
            <p>In reſpect of our ſelves we are to build God an Oratory; in reſpect of our parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer Families, we are to build him a Chappel: and if we have a larger circuit (if we be ſet in publick place) we are to build him a Church.</p>
            <p>This expreſſion of being <hi>built up</hi> (or <hi>building up our ſelves</hi>) implies 2. things.</p>
            <p n="1">1 To what end, or upon what terms or
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:47534:20"/>conditions we ought to come unto Chriſt; <hi>nempe ut in ipſo fundemut</hi> (Calvin) that we may be built up on him; <hi>to whom coming,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ye are built up, &amp;c.</hi> though Chriſt the living ſtone, be a moſt ſure and tried foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, a rock, and a rock of ages, yet he will bear no more, then God hath deſign'd him as a foundation to bear.</p>
            <p>It is a maxime of (the great Architect) Vitruvius, <hi>fundationes fodiantur ſi queant in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniri ad ſolidum &amp; in ſolido,</hi> let the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation be laid if it may be upon a ſolid rock: by which words, he commends to us (ſaith a learned Engliſh Commentator) not only a diligent, but even a jealous examination, what the foundation will bear.</p>
            <p>Though there be no other foundation but Chriſt, and though this foundation be infinitly ſufficient to beat the utmoſt weight that can <hi>regularly</hi> be laid on it; yet <hi>this foundation would ſink under the burden of the leaſt known ſin, unrepented of.</hi> They there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that come to him, (i. e.) who expect ſalvation by him) upon any other terms or condition, then being built up by obedience and conformity to him, by increaſing in vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and good works, inſtead of founding, doe but confound their own happineſſe.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2dly.</hi> This expreſſion of <hi>building up our ſelves</hi> (or being built up) implies that uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:47534:21"/>on in affection, that ſhould be between thoſe who are members of the ſame Church. An houſe built up, though the materials before the building (timber, ſtones, morter and the reſt) were divers and ſundry, yet are all ſo united that they become one. So in the ſpiritual houſe, though every particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler Chriſtian be an houſe (or Temple) for the holy Ghoſt to dwell in, yet by being built up all are united into one <hi>Baſilicon,</hi> or Princely fabrick.</p>
            <p>An <hi>Italian</hi> Architect (<hi>Leon Batiſta Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berti</hi>) is ſo curious in the point of union in a material fabrick, that he wiſheth that all the timber ſhould be cut out of the ſame forreſt, and all the ſtones dig'd out of the ſame quarry. This might not (probably) conduce more to the union of the houſe, then if the timber and ſtones were cut and dig'd out of divers forreſts, and quarryes. But (ſure I am) it conduceth not a little to the union of the ſpiritual houſe, that the timber and ſtones be cut and hewen out of the ſame forreſt and pit. For, when one ſaith <hi>I am of Paul,</hi> and another <hi>I am of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollos,</hi> and a third <hi>I am of Cephas,</hi> this gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to envy, ſtrife and diviſion, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, l <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3, 4.</p>
            <p>There are two things that tend much to the preſervation of this union.</p>
            <list>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:47534:21"/>
               <item>1. A Spirit of Contentation, with that eſtate and condition in which God hath plac'd every Member of the Church. For, as it tends to Schiſm in the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral body, if the foot ſhall envy the hand, or the ear the eye, or any of the members the head. If the foot ſhall ſay, why ſhould I bear the burthen of the whole, and not be ſupported as well as the head is? or the hand ſay, why ſhould I be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed as the inſtrument of action, and not partake with the eye, in its more honourable and eaſy imployment of ſpeculation? So in the ſpiritual body, if one member emulate or envy another, the Subject the Prince, the Presbyter the Biſhop, it muſt neceſſarily cauſe a cleft or ſchiſm in the building, which may ruin the whole. For, as in material buildings, all openings are weaknings; and therefore skilful builders adviſe that dores and windows be as few in number, and as moderate in dimenſion as may be. A ſpirit of contentation therefore is of a primary neceſſity to the preſervation of union.</item>
               <item>2. A Mutual Communication of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular faculties for the good of the whole. For, as the foot in the natural body can't
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:47534:22"/>refuſe to walk, the hand to work, or the eye to ſee, without the apparent preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of the whole. No more can any member in the ſpiritual fabrick, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold his particular ability from the reſt, without their detriment, and ſuffering loſſe by it. As when the members in the fable conſpired to withhold nouriſhment from the belly, they conſpired but their own ruine in weakning it. And as they obſerve in Architecture, it is a notorious ſoloeciſm to weaken that part, which muſt ſtrengthen all the reſt. But when every member communicates its particular fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty (the feet walk, the hands work, the eyes ſee, the ear hears, the tongue ſpeaks) this tends to the union of the whole, with the advantage of welfare to the particular members. And thus I have conſidered the Chriſtian Church as a ſpiritual houſe. Whence this infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence naturally may be drawn, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>There is a Maſter of this houſe, by whom the family ought to be ruled and Governed.</p>
            <p>It was an equitable and natural law, that King <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> made (upon his Queen <hi>Vaſhti's</hi> diſobedience) <hi>That every man ſhould bear Rule in his own houſe,</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:47534:22"/>Heſter i. ult. It is much more reaſonable, that God (the Maſter of this Spiritual Houſe) ſhould bear Rule in it. Our ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry being in Gods houſe, doth neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily oblige us to Subjection and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to him. When the Holy Ghoſt ſaith, ſuch or ſuch perſons were in ſuch, or ſuch an houſe, he intends ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection by it, <hi>Numb.</hi> 30.3. <hi>ult.</hi> Thus when the Iſraelites are ſaid to be in <hi>Pharoahs</hi> houſe, the meaning is, they were ſubject to him. <hi>Did I plainly appear unto the houſe of thy Father, when they were in</hi> Egypt <hi>in</hi> Pharaohs <hi>houſe?</hi> 1 Sam. 2.27. Let us therefore give up our ſelves conſciona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and ſincerely to the Government of our great Lord and Maſter.</p>
            <p>In things fundamental and eſſential to be believed and practiſed, we are to receive our direction from his lips only, as he ſpake by the mouths or pens of thoſe holy men, Prophets, and Apoſtles, who were inſpir'd by the Holy Ghoſt: Thus the Apoſtle expreſly, <hi>Though we, or an Angel from Heaven, Preach any other Goſpel unto you, then that which we have Preached unto you, let him he accurſed. As we ſaid before, ſo ſay I now again, if any man Preach any other Goſpel unto you, then
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:47534:23"/>that ye have received, let him be accurſed,</hi> Gal. 1.8, 9. where you have the Divine inviolable authority of the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture aſſerted; and a very dreadful ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence thundred againſt any perſon (of what rank or quality ſoever) that ſhall preſume to innovate, or introduce any Doctrine contrary to the Doctrine of thoſe holy Men, who ſpake as they were inſpir'd by the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Though we,</hi> i. e. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, and the Brethren that were with him, (in whoſe name he ſalutes the Churches of <hi>Galatia,</hi> ver. 2.) or <hi>though we,</hi> i. e. (as <hi>Vincent. Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinens.</hi>) <hi>etiamſi Petrus, etiamſi Andreas, etiamſi Joannes, etiamſi omnis Apoſtolorum chorus Evangelizet vobis praeterquam quod Evangelizavimus Anathema, ſit</hi> (l. 1. c. 12. <hi>praeſcript. adverſ. profan. haereſium novita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi>) Though <hi>Peter, Andrew, John,</hi> though the whole company of the Apoſtles, ſhould Preach to you any other Goſpel, then that which we have preached, let him be Anathema. <hi>Tremenda diſtrictio,</hi> a dreadful ſentence (ſaith he) yet <hi>parum eſt,</hi> this is but little in reſpect of that which followes, <hi>Though an Angel from Heaven ſhould Preach any other Goſpel unto you, let him be accurſed.</hi> Audite populi, tribus,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:47534:23"/>linguae, viri, mulieres, pueri, ſenes, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta gens Chriſtianorum Sancta (<hi>as</hi> Damaſ. Orat. 2. de imagin.) give ear, O ye people, tribes and tongues, men, wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, children, all the holy company that is called Chriſtians in all the world, <hi>Licet Angelus, licet Rex Evangelizet vobis praeter id quod accepi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>is, aures occludite.</hi> Though a King or Angel Preach any other Goſpel to you, then that ye have received, you are to ſtop your ears, and be as deaf unto his Doctrine.</p>
            <p>But here you muſt take heed of wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or miſunderſtanding the Apoſtles <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (<hi>praeter id,</hi> or <hi>praeterquam quod, then that which we have preached</hi>) for, this doth not confine the diſpenſers of the word, to a ſtrict obſervation of thoſe expreſſions and ſyllables only in their Adminiſtration, which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles uſed: they may (notwithſtanding this commination) uſe expreſſions of their own, (or borrow them from other profeſſions) in explicating, illuſtrating, or confirming the Truths of the Scripture. But the Apoſtles [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] is either to be interpreted <hi>contra</hi> (contrary to) as it is frequently uſed. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (in <hi>Ariſtot.</hi>) <hi>praeter,</hi> i. e. <hi>contra naturam
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:47534:24"/>&amp;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>praeter,</hi> i.e. <hi>contra legem</hi> (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, that is, contrary to nature. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the Law, that is contrary to it. Thus the prepoſition <hi>praeter</hi> is uſed likewiſe by <hi>Terence (in Andria) praeter civium morem atque legem,</hi> beſide, (that is contrary to) the Law and Cuſtom of Citizens. So St. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> explicates this Text. <hi>Non ait pluſquam accepiſtis, ſed praeterquam quod accepiſtis</hi> (<hi>Tract.</hi> 99. <hi>in Joan.</hi> he ſaith not more than you received, but other then, or beſide that which you have received: for (ſaith the Father) had he ſaid, <hi>more then you received,</hi> he had prejudiced himſelf, who deſired earneſtly to ſee the faces of his Theſſalonians, <hi>That he might perfect that, which was lacking in their faith,</hi> 1 Theſ. 3.10.</p>
            <p>Or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (other then that which you have received) <hi>quicquid Evangelio quaſi ad ſalutem neceſſarium additur (Parae.)</hi> whatſoever is added to the Goſpel, as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to ſalvation. I ſaid therefore we are to receive our direction from the Lips of God only in things <hi>Eſſential</hi> and <hi>Fundamental.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A fundamental (in general) is that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which other things are built. Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentalls in Religion, are thoſe primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:47534:24"/>truths, without the knowledge of which we can neither believe aright, nor yield that obedience which we owe to God. In theſe (I ſay) we are to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>depend upon God only for direction, to hear no voice but his, for (as they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve in Architecture) the yielding of a ſtone in the lower part of a Fabrick, but an hairs breadth, will make a cleft of more then half a foot aloft. So impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant are fundamental errors.</p>
            <p>A ſmall error in the beginning, and foundation of all things, proves in the procedure, and end of them a great miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief. And therefore God appointed the Foundation of the Tabernacle to be of maſſy pieces of ſilver; intimating there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the ſolidity and purity of the Truth, whereupon the Church is founded: And a <hi>Rabby</hi> of our own obſerves, that every man in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> from twenty years old and upward, was to give half a ſhekel towards theſe foundation-pieces; whereas to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things they were not bound to a ſet ſumme, but every man to give as his heart moved him, which might teach them, that to the Fundamentalls of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion they were all bound, but in other things, each one according to the gift
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:47534:25"/>given him; gold, or ſilver, or purple, or ſcarlet, or fine linnen, or goats hair, (<hi>Lightfoot</hi> on <hi>Exod.</hi> 30.) So that thus you ſee in things fundamental and eſſential, we are to receive directions from the great Maſter of the houſe, God only. But</p>
            <p>In things circumſtantial (even in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and the Worſhip of God) it is the maſters pleaſure, that we ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive directions in them, from his ſtew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards.</p>
            <p>The High Steward in this houſe (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God) is the King (or Higher Powers) intruſted by God with a legiſlative, and coercive (or conſtraining) power.</p>
            <p>By the <hi>Higher Powers</hi> I intend the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, not the office. And that by no leſs authority then St. <hi>Pauls,</hi> who calls (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) the <hi>Higher Powers,</hi> Rom. 13.1. at the 3d. verſe (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) Rulers.</p>
            <p>Now this higher, (or higheſt Power) is a ſingle perſon, or company of men, intruſted with Soveraign Power over the people, he, (or they) being ſubject only to the Empire or power of God himſelf. I ſay a ſingle perſon, or <hi>company of men:</hi> For though that which commands in
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:47534:25"/>chief, or in whom the higheſt Power is inveſted, muſt neceſſarily be one: yet it is not of neceſſity, that it be one in or by nature, but it ſufficeth, if it be one by inſtitution, ſo that the higheſt Power, is not appropriated to Kings, or abſolute Monarchs onely; but in a rightly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted Ariſtocracy or Common-wealth, the Optimates, Senat, Eſtates, (or by what other Title they are Dignified) are the higheſt Power: And they, or He, (the King) is only ſubject to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire of God himſelf. For, he is not, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not (in any propriety of ſpeech) be called the higheſt Power, but becauſe there is not among men, any higher Power. <hi>Super Imperatorem</hi> (ſaith Optatus contra Parmenianum l. 3.) <hi>Non eſt niſi ſolus Deus qui fecit Imperatorem.</hi> There is none ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour to the Emperour, but God only who made the Emperour. And ſo <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> (ad Scap.) <hi>Colimus Imperatorem ſic, quomodo &amp; nobis licet, &amp; ipſi e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pedit, ut ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minem a Deo ſecundum, &amp; ſolo Deo mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem.</hi> We ſo reverence the Emperour, as it is meet for him, and lawfull for us, as a man ſecond unto God, and inferiour to God only. You may perceive by this what I mean by <hi>the Higher Power;</hi> but
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:47534:26"/>ſince the good providence of God hath caſt; us under (the beſt of Governments) Monarchy, I ſhall ſpeak in the enſuing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe concerning the ſingle perſon, the King only. And</p>
            <p n="1">1. He is intruſted by God, with Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and Power, not only in Civill matters, and affairs of State; but <hi>in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall matters, the Affaires of Religion in the Church.</hi> There are 3. Arguments that evince this.</p>
            <p n="1">1. St. Paul tells you, Rom. 13.4. <hi>He is the Miniſter of God to thee for good.</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) indefinitely, univerſally. And explicating himſelf afterward more diſtinctly, he tells us that Kings (and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in eminent, or the higheſt place <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) were inſtituted and appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of God to this end and purpoſe, <hi>that we ſhould lead a quiet and peaceable life un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them, not only in all honeſty, but in all piety,</hi> 1 Tim. 2.2. The happineſs of a City, Country, or Kingdom, conſiſts in this, <hi>ut Dei ſit amans, &amp; amata Deo,</hi> That it love, and be beloved of God. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t illum ſibi Regem, ſe illius populum agnoſcat.</hi> (Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt. de Civit. Dei l. 5. c. 14.) That it be in ſubjection to God, whom it hath over it for its King. And the Father-pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:47534:26"/>Kings happy, <hi>Si ſuam poteſtatem ad Dei cultum maxime dilatandum, Majeſtati ejus famulam faciant.</hi> If by promoting his worſhip as far as they can, they ſubject their power to the Majeſty of God.</p>
            <p>Thus the Emperours <hi>Theodoſius</hi> and <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norius (Epiſt. ad Marcellinum)</hi> tell him, that they deſign'd not any thing in all their Labour of War, and Councells of Peace, <hi>Niſi ut verum Dei cultum, orbis noſtri plebs devota custodiat;</hi> That the people devoted to their ſervice, might follow the right worſhip of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theodoſius</hi> likewiſe <hi>(in Ep. ad Cyrillum) Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarei eſt muneris, ut non ſolum pacifice, ſed pie etiam ſubditi vivant,</hi> The Emperour muſt take care that his Subjects live under him, not only peaceably, but piouſly. Thus <hi>Iſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor Peluſiota</hi> propounds the ſame end to the Prince as to the Prieſt. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The Salvation of their Subjects; to which that of <hi>Ammianus Marcellinus</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees fully, <hi>Nihil aliud eſt imperium (ut ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entes definiunt) niſi cura ſalutis alienae.</hi> (<hi>l.</hi> 39.) Empire is nothing elſe (in the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of wiſe men) but the care of the Welfare and Salvation of others. Since then this is the end which Kings are to propound unto themſelves, that their
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:47534:27"/>Subjects may live under them, not onely honeſtly, but godly; it neceſſarily fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, that they muſt be intruſted with Authority and Power in Eccleſiaſticall matters. For, the end being admitted, we muſt admit thoſe things without which the end cannot be attain'd. And accordingly we find God laying his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand upon Kings in Scripture. <hi>When the King ſitteth upon the Throne of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, he ſhall write him a Copy of this Law in a book, out of that which is before the Prieſts and the Levites, and it ſhall be with him, and he ſhall read therein, all the dayes of his life, that he may learn to fear the Lord his God,</hi> Deut. 17.18, 19. <hi>and</hi> Pſal. 2.10, 11. <hi>Be wiſe now therefore Oye Kings; ſerve the Lord with fear, and rejoyce with trembling</hi> If you will admit St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon this Text, he will tell you how Kings, as Kings, ſerve God. <hi>Si in ſuo regno bona jubeant, mala prohibeant, non ſolum quae pertinent ad humanam ſocietatem, verum etiam quae pertinent ad divinam reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gionem.</hi> (contra Creſcon. l. 3. c. 51.) when they command thoſe things to be done which are good, and prohibit evill actions, not only in things appertaining to humane ſociety, but in things appertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:47534:27"/>to Religion. And yet more fully and expreſly, <hi>Quomodo ergo Reges Domino ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt in timore, niſi ea quae contra juſſa Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni fiunt, religioſa ſeveritate prohibendo atque pleciendo?</hi> (Ep. ad Bonifac.) How do Kings ſerve the Lord in fear, but by a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere prohibition, and puniſhment of thoſe things which are contrary to the Command of God? <hi>Aliter enim ſervit, qua homo eſt, aliter, qua Rexeſt, &amp;c.</hi> For he ſerves the Lord after a different manner as he is a King, from that in which he ſerves him as a Man. He ſerves him as a Man by living faithfully, as a King by enacting Good and Wholſome Laws, for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting of Virtue and Piety, and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Vice. So King <hi>Hezekias</hi> ſerved the Lord, by deſtroying the Idol-Temples and Groves. So <hi>Joſias</hi> ſerved him like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. So the King of <hi>Nineveh</hi> ſerved him, in proclaming a Faſt to be univerſally obſerved for appeaſing the divine diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. Kings ſerve God as Kings, when they doe that in order to the ſervice of God, which unleſs they were Kings they could not do. And herein is that promiſe of God to his Church; <hi>That Kings ſhould be her Nurſing Fathers, and their Queens her Nurſing Mothers,</hi> made good, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.23.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:47534:28"/>
2dly. That Kings are intruſted with the affairs of Religion appears further, becauſe St. <hi>Paul</hi> tels us, <hi>the King is the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of God, to execute wrath upon him that doth evil,</hi> Rom. 13.4. <hi>as the good</hi> in the former Argument; So <hi>the evill</hi> in this, being indefinitely expreſs'd, and having the force of an univerſall, it muſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend all evill, even in Eccleſiaſticall, as well as Civill things. Thus the wiſeſt of Kings <hi>(Solomon)</hi> tells us, <hi>A King that ſitteth on the Throne of Judgement ſcatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth away all evill with his eyes,</hi> Prov. 20.8. Thus the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> engage them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to <hi>Joſhua</hi> (the chiefe Magiſtrate) <hi>according as we hearkened unto Moſes in all things, ſo will we hearken unto thee.</hi> Joſh. 1.17. Thus the Fathers argue from thoſe words of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 13.1. <hi>Let every ſoul be ſubject unto the Higher Powers.</hi> If every ſoul, then Eccleſiaſticall perſons as well as others. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>(Theophil.)</hi> though he be a Prieſt, or an Apoſtle; and ſo St. <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> though an Evangeliſt, though an Apoſtle, though a Prophet, every one ought to be ſubject. And <hi>Bernard</hi> (treading in their ſteps) <hi>ſi omnis, &amp; veſtra, quis vos excipit ab univerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate?</hi> Ep. ad Archiepiſc.) if every ſoul
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:47534:28"/>ought to be ſubject, then yours; for who hath excepted you from the univerſall, <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſoul?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither will Reaſon admit that any perſon ſhould be exempted. For, he who would be exempted, would either not be ſubject to any humane power at all, or to ſome other power beſides the Supreme. He who would not be ſubject to any, doth thereby unavoidably introduce a mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt confuſion, of which <hi>God is not the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor,</hi> 1 Cor. 14.33.</p>
            <p>He who would be ſubject to ſome other power beſides the Supreme, doth as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily introduce two Superiour powers, which is a thing unnaturall, and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent. <hi>Ea enim eſt ſummi conditio, ut nihil aliud adaequet, nedum ſuperet</hi> (Tertul.) Such is the condition of the Supream power, that it cannot admit a Superiour or E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual. By this Argument the primitive Fathers overthrew the Gentiles Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſme: Becauſe, <hi>That which is higheſt can be but one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as in man, there is one will, which commands the motions, and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of every member; ſo in the Church, there can be but one which muſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. Which will be made evident
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:47534:29"/>by reflecting upon the effects of Empire or Government which are obligation to duty, and compulſion to perform. If therefore there ſhould be more Superiour powers then one, their commands might be contrary one to another; and ſo the ſubject leſt without a poſſibility of yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing obedience to the one, without incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the diſpleaſure of the other.</p>
            <p>And if any man ſhall ſay that the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons being divers (namely Civill, Milita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and Eccleſiaſticall) the chiefe power may be divided alſo into ſundry perſons. It would follow from hence, that the ſame perſon, at the ſame time, might be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by one to go unto the Market, by another to the Camp, by a third to Church; and ſo put under an impoſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of obeying either. Whence all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions have (by the light of nature) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected plurality in Government. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (Homer) <hi>&amp; omnis poteſtas impatiens conſortis.</hi> The Throne can no more brook a Rival then the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage Bed. This our Lord Chriſt hath put beyond diſpute, when he tells us, <hi>No man can ſerve two Maſters,</hi> Mat 6.24.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly. Not to multiply Arguments in proof of that, which would ſtand in
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:47534:29"/>need of little, had not that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious proud Spirit which poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed <hi>Donatus,</hi> entred into ſome Men, occaſioning them to ſay (as he did in Optatus l. 3.) <hi>Quid Imperatori cum eccleſia?</hi> What hath the King to doe with the Church.</p>
            <p>The Third (and laſt) Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall be drawn from the joynt Suffrage and Teſtimony of all Nations, not onely Chriſtian, but Heathen, bearing witneſſe to the Power and Authority of Kings in Eccleſiaſticall affaires; (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it appeares to be no other then the dictate of Right Reaſon, which is common to the humane intellectuall Nature. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> (Polit. 7.8.) ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, The care of Princes ought to be firſt of all for the Things of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>The Twelve Tables (the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of the Roman Law) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain in them many Things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Religion.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:47534:30"/>
               <l>Jus triplex, tabulae quod ter ſanxere quadratae,</l>
               <l>Sacrum, privatum, &amp; populi commune quod uſquam eſt.</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>(Anſon.)</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>You have in theſe a taſte of the Heathens Judgement concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this. (And one need not drink up the Sea to know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be Salt, or not.)</p>
            <p>For the Ancient Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, that of <hi>Socrates</hi> (the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorian) may ſtand for many. <hi>Ex quo Imperatores facti ſunt Chriſtiani, res Eccleſiae ab. ipſis dependiſſe.</hi> The affaires of Religion depended upon the Emperours, ever ſince they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Chriſtian. Which <hi>Optatus</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms, when he ſaith, <hi>Non e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim respublica eſt in Eccleſia, ſed Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia in republica,</hi> i. e. <hi>in Romano Imperio.</hi> (l. 3.) For the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Wealth is not in the Church, but the Church in the Common-Wealth, that is, in the Roman Empire. <hi>Conſtantine</hi> (in an anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent inſcription) is ſtiled, <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gionis &amp; Fidei Auctor.</hi> The Increaſer
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:47534:30"/>of Faith and Religion. And <hi>Baſilius</hi> the Emperour ſpeaking of the Church as a Ship, <hi>Ejus ſibi gvbernacula ait a Deo concredita.</hi> Saith that God hath committed the Sterage (or Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) of it, to him.</p>
            <p>And there is an Ancient E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle of <hi>Elutherius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> in which he ſtiles the King of <hi>England, (vicarium Dei in regno ſuo, agens de negotio Religionis.</hi>) Gods vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car for the management of the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of Religion in his Kingdome, and the firſt <hi>Moguntine</hi> Councel, calls <hi>Charles</hi> the Great <hi>(Vere Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligionis Rectorem)</hi> the Rector of the True Religion; and as they of old, ſo the Reformed Churches of late, were of the ſame perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in this particular. As it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by their reſpective confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>(<hi>Magiſtratum eſt, non modo de ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vili politia eſſe ſollicitos, verum eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am dare operam, ut Sacrum Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterium conſervetur, Chriſtique Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num propagetur; denique horum eſt efficere, ut Sacrum Evangelii ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum undique praedicetur: ut ſinguli
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:47534:31"/>purae Deum colere, &amp; venerari ex praeſcripto verbi ipſius libere poſſint.</hi> Belgica.) It is the Magiſtrates Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, not only to be careful for the Civil Politie, but to endeavour like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe that the Sacred Miniſtry be Preſerved, and the Kingdom of Chriſt Propagated. It is his duty (finally) to ſee that the Holy Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel be every where Preached, and that all perſons may purely and freely worſhip, and ſerve God, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his word. And ſo the latter Helvetian Confeſſion. <hi>(Teneat ipſe Magiſtratus in manibus verbum Dei, &amp; ne huic contrarium doceatur procuret, bonis legibus ad verbum Dei compoſitis, moderetur populum ſibi a Deo concreditum.</hi>) Let the Magiſtrate take into his hands the World of God, and take care nothing be taught contrary to it: And let him Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern the people committed to him of God, by good and wholeſome Lawes, according to the word of God.</p>
            <p>And the Confeſſion of <hi>Baſil</hi> (wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſome others) <hi>Quilibet Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus Magistratus, omnes vires eo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riget,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:47534:31"/>ut apud fidei ſuae commiſſos, nomen Dei ſanctificetur, regnum ipſius propagetur, ipſiuſque voluntati cum ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria extirpatione ſcelerum vivatur. Hoc officium gentili Magiſiratui injunctum fuit, quanto magis Chriſtiano Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stratui commendatum eſſe debeat, ut vero Dei vicario?</hi>) It ought to be the Serious Endeavour of every Chriſtian Magiſtrate, that the name of God be Hallowed, and his Kingdom Propogated among thoſe who are commited to his Truſt: and that they live, denying all ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs according to his Will. This was a <hi>Duty</hi> incumbent on the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Magiſtrate; how much more ought it to be commended to the Chriſtian Magiſtrate, <hi>as the True Vicar of Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or Church of <hi>England</hi> deems thoſe worthy of Excommunication, who deny unto our Kings, the ſame Power and Authority in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Cauſes, that the Pious Kings of the <hi>Hebrews</hi> Exerciſed in the Church of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> (Canon the 2d.)</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:47534:32"/>
And here we muſt neceſſarily enquire how far the Authority of the King Extends in matters of Religion: whether we are to obey him in every thing he commands without exception, or but in ſome things only.</p>
            <p>We do not believe the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the King Extends ſo far, as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſtretcheth the <hi>Popes,</hi> when he ſaith, <hi>Si papa erraret prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipiendo vitia, vel prohibendo virtutes, teneretur Eccleſia credere vitia eſſe bona, &amp; virtutes malas.</hi> (de Rom. pont. l. 4. c. 5.) If the <hi>Pope</hi> ſhould erre in commanding Vice, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding Vertue, the Church is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to believe, that Vice is good, and Vertue is evil.</p>
            <p>We extend not the power of the King, as certain Religious Perſons, (who left it as a Rule to their confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents at <hi>Padova,</hi> 1606.) did the <hi>Popes</hi> authority. <hi>Si quod occulis noſtris album apparet, nigrum ille eſſe definierit, debemus itidem quod nigrum ſit pronuntiare.</hi> If that which in our eye is white be defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n'd by the <hi>Pope</hi> to be black, we ought
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:47534:32"/>alſo to ſay that it is black. But this we ſay, our obedience is required to all his commands that are not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to the law of nature, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Expreſs Word of God. If he command any thing forbidden by the Law of Nature, or by any Poſitive Law of God (that is now ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging to Chriſtians) or if he forbid any thing Commanded of God, we are not to yield obedience. For as in nature, inferiour cauſes depending in point of activity upon Superiour, have no power of acting contrary to the efficacy of the Superiour: So in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality, as St. Auguſt. <hi>Si aliud Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator, aliud jubeat Deus, quid judicatur? major pote<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tas Deus, da veniam O Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perator.</hi> (<hi>de verb. Dom:</hi> Sec: Mat: Serm: 6:) Where the Emperors, and Gods Commands are one contrary to the other, what Judgement ſhall I make? the power of God is Supream, the Emperour therefore muſt be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicated to pardon me.</p>
            <p>If the King Command any thing that God forbids, or forbid any thing that God Commands, in both
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:47534:33"/>theſe caſes, we muſt then fortifie our ſelves with the ſaying of St: <hi>Peter,</hi> and the other Apoſtles, <hi>We ought to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey God rather then men,</hi> Acts 5: 29: And God having by nature prohibit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the killing of an Innocent perſon, the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Midwives are commended for not obeying the Kings comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement concerning the killing of the male children: <hi>But the Midwives fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed God</hi> (ſaith the Text) <hi>and did not as the King of</hi> Egypt <hi>commanded them,</hi> Exod: 1: 17.</p>
            <p>Whatever a commandement of God makes neceſſary, no humane authority can render not neceſſary or obliging, and therefore it is uſually ſaid that the Goſpel, Miniſtry, and Sacraments, are not ſubject to any humane Authority; that is, in point of changing or alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that in them, which is of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Inſtitution. For, what God hath Determined Affirmatively, or Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, man cannot determine the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. But in things not determined by God, as Time, Place, and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of performing actions comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by God, the King by his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:47534:33"/>may determine theſe. Though the King cannot Prohibite an Holy, Harmleſs, rightly conſtituted Miniſtry, the Preaching of the Word, or Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring the Sacrament, according to the form of Divine Inſtitution: yet he may require them to preach at ſuch times, and in ſuch places only; he may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe them the habit in which they ſhall Officiate, by Vertue of that Apoſtolicall Precept: <hi>Let all things be done Decently, and in Order,</hi> 1 Cor. 14. ult. This Rule is ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitable, that all men will yield their aſſent, <hi>That all things in the Worſhip of God ought to be done De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently, and in Order.</hi> But what is <hi>Decent,</hi> and <hi>Orderly,</hi> is not ſo ſoon agreed. For that (ſaith one) which you call <hi>Decent,</hi> is, (in my Opinion) the moſt <hi>unſeemly</hi> thing in the world. And that is moſt <hi>diſorderly</hi> (in my Judgement) which you account <hi>Regularly</hi> performed, and in <hi>Order.</hi> There muſt therefore be ſome proper Judge agreed upon to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine what is <hi>Decent,</hi> and in <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der:</hi> Do you then Judge in your ſelves, (laying only your Prejudice
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:47534:34"/>and Paſſion aſide) whether a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Man, or Maſter of a Great Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, leaving this general Rule for the Government of his houſe, that all things in it be done <hi>Decently</hi> and in <hi>Order,</hi> doth he not intend and expect that his Steward ſhould De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine what is ſo? For either the Steward, or the reſt of the Servants muſt determine it. If the Servants, confuſion and ataxy, inſtead of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency and Order, muſt inavoidable flow in upon them. For one will ſay this is decent, and another the contrary is decent. It is more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent ſaith one to put off our ſhoes then our hats, in Reſpect and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence to our Lord, it is more or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly to ſit then to ſtand in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. This muſt neceſſarily beget Partyes and Sidings, that Animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, Strife, and Contention, and by conſequence the ruine of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily. For why (will one ſervant in the Family, or one party, ſay) ſhould not I, or we, judge of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency as well as you, or your party? So that you cannot but ſee that there is a neceſſity that the Steward
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:47534:34"/>ſhould Determine. And is it not thus in the Spiritual houſe? If every Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, or Paſtor, be left free to judge of what is Decent and in Order, things as unreaſonable as the putting off the ſhoes, and ſitting in the Maſters preſence will be practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the moſt: Becauſe <hi>the moſt are not the wiſeſt. And they affect ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally like Cattle fallen into a River, to Swim againſt the Stream.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In things therefore of this nature (namely ſuch as are not determined by the great Maſter, God) you owe obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Stewards determination, eſpecially ſince whatſoever is not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden by God, hath in that very reſpect, the force of a permiſſion at leaſt. Becauſe, <hi>Where there is no Law, there is no tranſgreſſion,</hi> Rom. 4.15. Now there is no Law againſt ſuch or ſuch indifferent things and therefore he who conforms, ſins not. But there is a Law which requires <hi>Every Soul to be ſubject to the Higher Powers,</hi> Rom. 13.1. He therefore that conforms not, ſins. You ought therefore to be ſubject to the Higher Power in matters of Religion for
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:47534:35"/>Conſcience Sake. But if any man will not be ſubject for Conſcience Sake, he muſt be ſubject upon another account, for God hath entruſted the Supreme Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate with a <hi>Coercive Power.</hi> Which is the 2d. thing propounded to be made good.</p>
            <p>In purſuance of this 2. thing,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>There ought to be ſome Coercive Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in Eccleſiaſticall Things, or Matters of Religion.</hi> For, without this every man would be left free, to ſpeak or do what him lift. To introduce any falſe or blaſphemous Opinion, to diſturb the Peace of the Church, by enormous Practices. May not one deny the Divine Authority of the Scriptures? Another the Divinity of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt? A third reject, deſpiſe and trample under foot the Prieſtly Office, and all the Ordinances of the Goſpell? And (for practice) might not men (with the evill Servant in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell) <hi>eat and drink with the drunken, and ſmite their fellow Servants with the Fiſt of Violence?</hi> Oppreſſing and Perſecuting all that are not of their Opinion, though their Opinion be not at any agreement, or conſiſtency with the truth. If there
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:47534:35"/>be not <hi>a Coercive Power</hi> ſtated ſomewhere, who or what ſhall hinder theſe, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable other inconveniences and miſchiefs?</p>
            <p>Every Fanatick Spirit, if there were no coercive power, might take licence by reviving old Hereſies, or broach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing worſe new invented Opinions, to ruffle the Church, and reduce it to an Heap or Chaos of Confuſion. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a coercive power ſomewhere ſtated, all Reins of Government, muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily be let looſe, and an effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all dore ſet open for Atheiſme, Hereſy, Sedition and Blaſphemy to enter in. But this is a thing ſo contrary, not only to the peace, but even to the eſſence of all ſocieties, that none but the abſolute Sons of <hi>Belial,</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Yoke) can plead for it. I paſſe therefore from that (as a thing aſſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto by all that pretend to Reaſon,) <hi>That there muſt be a Coercive Power?</hi> and come unto the 2d. thing the ſubject of this Power, or Perſon in whom it is. <hi>And that is the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Him hath God entruſted with co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercive Power in Matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:47534:36"/>
Spirituall Power, (or Power in the Church) is divided generally into <hi>Ordinis,</hi> and <hi>Juriſdictionis.</hi> That <hi>of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> is referr'd to the preaching or the Word, Adminiſtration of Sacraments, Abſolution, Confirmation, and all ſuch Actions, as a perſon regularly ordained performes by Virtue of his Orders.</p>
            <p>That of <hi>Juriſdiction</hi> is double, <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall,</hi> and <hi>Externall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Internall.</hi> Where the Spirituall guides, they who have the conduct of the Soules of men, by Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, Perſwaſion, Ghoſtly Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, and ſuch like; ſo convince the inward Conſciences of Men, that they become wholly obedient to their directions. As Saint <hi>Peter</hi> by his Sermon wrought upon the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of thoſe Jews, <hi>Who were pricked in their Heart, and ſaid, Men, and Brethren what ſhall we do?</hi> Acts 2.37.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Externall.</hi> Where the Perſon in whom the Power is (<hi>in foro exteriori,</hi> as they ſpeak) compells the Chriſtians obedience. The King is not intruſted with the firſt and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:47534:36"/>2d. of theſe. He hath no Power <hi>of Order,</hi> nor Juriſdiction <hi>over the Inner Man,</hi> but in things that are for the outward Politie of the Church (as that God may be tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſerved, ſuch as tranſgreſſe the received lawfull conſtitutions of the Church puniſhed) with this Power the King is intruſted.</p>
            <p>Again, the Actions of Men, are either <hi>Internall or Externall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Internall</hi> Actions abſtractedly, and ſimply conſidereed in themſelves, doe not fall under any humane Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority or Power whatſoever. <hi>Errat ſi quis putet ſervitutem in totum ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minem deſcendere; pars enim melior excepta eſt. Corpora obnoxia ſunt, &amp; adſcripta Dominis, mens ſui juris eſt.</hi> (Sen. de Benef. l. 3.) It is an Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour in any man to think that Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitude deſcends upon the whole man, for the better part, is alwayes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted: Our bodies indeed are Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxnious to Servitude, and the pleaſure of thoſe who are Lords o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us, but our minds are free, and at their own diſpoſe.</p>
            <p>And it is a known ſaying in the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:47534:37"/>Law, <hi>Cogitationis paenam nemo patitur:</hi> No man ſuffers any thing for his bare thoughts. For, All Empire (or Power) neceſſarily ſuppoſeth ſuch matter, as is capable of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under the knowledge of him that commands, but the internall Actions of Men Simply and Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractedly conſidered, doe not come under the knowledge of any Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Power, and therefore they fall not under their Authority. No power can impoſe upon any perſon that he ſhall think thus, and not otherwiſe, concerning any Article of Faith, becauſe he cannot know whether a man thinks ſo or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. As Lactantius (l. 5. c. 13.) <hi>Quis mihi imponat neceſſitatem vel cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendi quod nolim, vel quod velim non credendi?</hi> Who can compell me to believe what I will not, or not to believe what I liſt? For, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligio imperari non poteſt.</hi> Religion can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be compell'd (as Caſſidor. l. 3. Ep. 27.) and <hi>Fides ſuadenda, non imperanda el.</hi> (Bern. Serm. 66. in Cant.) you may allure, you can't compell any man to believe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:47534:37"/>
But, beſides theſe <hi>Internal,</hi> there are <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal</hi> actions, the words, and works of men: and theſe fall under Humane Authority, and Power; thus the Emperours, <hi>Gratian, Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentinian,</hi> and <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> ſpeak concerning a man, that is an Heretick, <hi>Sibi tantummodo nocitura ſentiat, aeliis obfutura non pandat.</hi> If he will think evil things, he ſhall ſurmiſe them to himſelf onely: he ſhall not publiſh them to the hurt of others And it was with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to this, that <hi>Conſtantine</hi> ſtiled himſelf (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>a Biſhop in thoſe things, that are without.</hi> Though therefore the Prince cannot compel men to believe this, or that, yet he may compel them, not to make Profeſſion of any other Faith, then that which he allows, or approves. Thus the King of <hi>Nineveh</hi> enjoyned his Subjects <hi>Sackcloth, Faſting, Prayer, and turning from the Violence in their hands</hi> (<hi>Jonah</hi> 3.8.) and indeed there's nothing, in which the Supreme power conſiſts more, then in determining the Publick Exerciſe of Religion. All, that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of Politicks, make this <hi>Praecipuum inter Majeſtatis jura,</hi> a Principal Jewel of the Crown: to this every man's Reaſon ſubſcribes. For, if it be demanded, why in the land of our Nativity (this Kingdom) the <hi>Roman</hi> Religion flouriſhed in the days of Queen
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:47534:38"/>
               <hi>Mary,</hi> and the Evangelical (or Reformed) in the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth?</hi> The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ximate cauſe of it muſt be acknowledged the will, and pleaſure of the reſpective Queens. Or, if it be asked, why one way of Worſhip is uſed by the <hi>French,</hi> and <hi>Spaniard,</hi> and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other by the <hi>Dane,</hi> and <hi>Swed?</hi> you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not anſwer any thing, but the will of thoſe, that Rule over them.</p>
            <p>If it be objected againſt this, that ſuch a Power in the <hi>Prince</hi> would render the <hi>State</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> unſtable, and mutable: <hi>Religion</hi> being ſubject to be changed, as oft as the Prince ſhould change his mind. It muſt be acknowleged true: but,</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Danger is as great in other things, and reſpects; the Work always an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering the Artificer: and <hi>qualis Rex, talis lex;</hi> ſuch as the King is, ſuch are his Laws. But no perſon may have his right denyed him, for fear leaſt he ſhould abuſe it: for no man whatſoever ſhould (upon this account) have his right in any thing; becauſe it is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for him to abuſe it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Suppoſing the right poſsible to be transferred from the Supreme Magiſtrate, to ſome other, the danger and inconvenience would be no leſs. For, upon whomſoever it be transferred, they, who muſt Manage this
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:47534:38"/>Power, are men, and ſo fallible, and ſubject to mutability. Our onely hope, &amp; comfort in this caſe, is in the Divine Providence: the minds of all men being in the power of God to confirm them in the truth, or to ſuffer them to turn from the truth to a ly; but the hearts of Kings more eſpecially, according to that of <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, The Kings heart is in the hand of the Lord, as the Rivers of water</hi> (<hi>Prov.</hi> 21.1.) God can, and doth, carry on his own work, both by good, and evil Kings, well knowing, that a Tempeſt is ſometimes more neceſſary, and profitable for his Church, then a Calm. If he, that rules, be a Pious Prince, converſant in the Scripture, frequent in Prayer, alover of the Church, one, that enclines his ear to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of thoſe, who are truly Pious, and Learned, the Truth proſpers and prevails mightily un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Him; but, if He be a Perſon of a perverſe ſpirit, and corrupt judgment, He proves an heavy ſcourge to thoſe, that are in ſubjection under Him; <hi>Et legibus malis probantur boni, &amp; legibus bonis emendantur mali,</hi> (<hi>Auguſt. adverſ. Creſcentium,</hi> l. 3. c. 51.) Evil Laws are for the probation of Good men, as good Laws for the emendation of Evil men. The <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church ſaw frequent mutations in their Worſhip: <hi>Hezekiah</hi> aboliſhed the Idol-Worſhip of hs Father <hi>Ahaz,</hi> his Grand-childe
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:47534:39"/>
               <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> reſtored it again, and <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah,</hi> his Grand-childs, aboliſhed in a ſecond time: and yet the Right of their Kings was never diſputed. For, <hi>It was never lawfull for the People to aſſume unto themſelves the Publick Exerciſe of Religion by force:</hi> but, if they cannot conſcionably conform to it, they may Pray, and Weep, and Fly: other wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons Chriſtianity allows them not. Thus the Prophet <hi>Elijah</hi> fled from <hi>Ahab,</hi> and thus our Lord <hi>Chriſt</hi> indulgeth (if he doth not Counſel) his Apoſtles, ſaying, <hi>When they perſecute you in this City, flee ye into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Matt.</hi> 10.23. Thus St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſius,</hi> delivered themſelves by flight, in the time of Perſecution; and the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> who lived under the rage and fury of <hi>Julian,</hi> knew nothing but the water, that diſtilled from their own eyes, to quench the fire of that Perſecution. <hi>Aliud contra Perſecutorem non erat remedium: ultra nefas procedere.</hi> (<hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zian. Orat.</hi> in <hi>Julianum.</hi>) They knew no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther remedy againſt their perſecutors: to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed any further was villany. <hi>Coactus, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnare non novi, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lere potero, flere potero, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mere potero; aliter nec debeo, nec poſſum reſiſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. (Ambr.)</hi> I know not how to reſiſt, being conſtrained: I can weep, and grieve, and mourn; otherwiſe I neither can, nor ought
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:47534:39"/>to reſiſt. And this they did, not (as ſome have vainly dreamed) becauſe they were deſtitute of Power to make reſiſtance: For, (as <hi>Tertullian,</hi> in his Apology, ſaith of them) <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbes, Inſulas,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Palatium, Senatum, Forum impleverant;</hi> the Cities, Iſlands, Caſtles, Garriſons, Judgment-Seats, Palace, and Senat were full of them, and yet (as he) <hi>Nulli Albiniani, nulli Nigriani, nulli Caſſiani,</hi> there were no Traitors, or Rebels, much leſs King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>killers among them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Euſebius Pius</hi> (the Biſhop of <hi>Samoſatia</hi>) being baniſhed by the command of <hi>Valens</hi> the Emperour, the people would have held him in his Epiſcopal See by force: but he, having learned the Apoſtle's leſſon, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. taught them alſo, what Reverence, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, was due to the Emperour's commands; and telling them, that he would not (if he could) ſecure himſelf by a multitude, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſsing him about <hi>(Nec ego me vallabo, inquit, circumfuſione populorum)</hi> he thereby ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed an imminent ſedition. Theſe (and many more Examples at hand) do abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly evidence what deep impreſsion the words of <hi>Chriſt</hi> to <hi>Peter</hi> made upon the ſpirits of Chriſtians heretofore. The words of <hi>Chriſt</hi> are, <hi>Put up again thy ſword into its place: for all they, that take the ſword, ſhall periſh with the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:47534:40"/>ſword;</hi> Matt. 26.52. <hi>Arripit autem, qui non a Deo accipit: dedit autem Deus ſoli ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae poteſtati, aliis, non niſi per illam.</hi> (Grot.) He takes the ſword, (namely with an hand of violence) who doth not receive it from God: for God hath given it onely to the <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Power,</hi> and to others by him. Thus then you ſee the determining of the Publick exerciſe of Religion is inveſted in the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Power. And it is no leſs the Prince's Duty, to aboliſh, or puniſh all falſe Worſhip, or Religion. Thus <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> (in <hi>Babylon</hi>) being convinced of the Divinity of the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> made a capital Law againſt the blaſphemers of his Name. <hi>Therefore I make a Decree, that every People, Nation, and Language, which ſpeak any thing amiſs againſt the God of Shadrach,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſhall be cut in pieces, and their houſes ſhall be made a dunghill.</hi> (<hi>Dan.</hi> 3.29.) <hi>Darius</hi> (of the <hi>Medes,</hi> and <hi>Perſians</hi>) En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted a Royal Law to the ſame import. <hi>I make a Decree, that in every Dominion of my Kimgdom, men tremble, and fear, before the God of Daniel, for he is the living God.</hi> (<hi>Dan.</hi> 6.26.) In <hi>Athens</hi> they had a Law againſt (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) Irreligion: upon which three fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Philoſophers (<hi>Socrates, Theodorus,</hi> and <hi>Protagoras</hi>) ſuffered. <hi>Socrates,</hi> (as <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ertius</hi> reports in his Life) was accuſed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>)
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:47534:40"/>of Irreligion, and the Action Commenced againſt him in theſe words, (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.) <hi>Socrates</hi> is a tranſgreſſor, in not eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe for Gods, whom the City eſteems ſuch; but brings in other new Gods of his own. And all this was done onely by virtue of the Supreme Power reſiding in them. For, though every Maſter of a Family be obliged to remove Idols, and every thing of falſe Worſhip, out of his own Private Family: yet the King (or perſons delegated by him) may onely do it in the Publick.</p>
            <p>There is a Text indeed in <hi>Deuteronomy,</hi> that ſeems to countenance private perſons, in deſtroying of Idols, and falſe Worſhip. <hi>Ye ſhall deſtroy their Altars, and break down their Images, &amp; cut down their Groves, and burn their Graven Images with fire</hi> (<hi>Deut.</hi> 7.5.) But, if St. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> may be admitted to Comment upon the Text, he tells you, that they might not do it, without Authority from the Higher Powers. <hi>Cumacceperitis poteſtatem, hoc facite: ubi non eſt data nobis poteſtas, non facimus.</hi> (<hi>Serm.</hi> 6. <hi>de verb. Dom. ſec. Mat.</hi>) You may do this, when you have received Authority, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Authority we do it not. Hence <hi>Nicepho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> reprehends, and condemns <hi>Abdas</hi> the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:47534:41"/>for demoliſhing the <hi>Perſians</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Temple, in which they Worſhipped the Fire; which proved a matter of much inconvenience, and trouble to the Chriſtians. The <hi>Pagan</hi> Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, in the City of <hi>Rome,</hi> were not ſhut up by the Chriſtians, till <hi>Conſtantine</hi> made a Law a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them. And the <hi>Elibertine</hi> Councel (<hi>An.</hi> 305.) provides by a Canon <hi>(Si quis Idolum fregerit, &amp; ibidem occiſus fuerit, ne in Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrum numerum recipiatur)</hi> that, if any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon be killed for breaking an Idol in pieces, he ſhall not be enrolled among the Martyrs of the Church; becauſe (ſaith the Councel) <hi>(Neque in Evangelio ſcriptum ſit, neque ab A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolis factum reperiatur)</hi> we have neither precept in Scripture, nor example of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles to countenance the Fact. And thus you ſee <hi>The Supreme Magiſtrate is entruſted with a Coercive Power in matters of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Reaſon why he is entruſted with this Power is, Becauſe, without this, he would bear the Sword in vain. The Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, that <hi>he beareth not the Sword in vain.</hi> (<hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4.) The Sword (ſaith <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phylact</hi>) is the Coercive Power, (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) and he bears it not in vain (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) but that he may puniſh Evil-doers.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:47534:41"/>
It is a thing to be wiſhed, to be beg'd of Heaven, with our moſt Fervent Prayers, that all Chriſtians might be like thoſe in the <hi>Acts, of one Minde, and of one Soul:</hi> that all, who confeſs God's Holy Name, ſhould agree in the Truth of his Holy Word (as our Church teacheth us to Pray) but the peeviſhneſs of ſome, the intereſt, and malice of others, renders this a thing ſcarcely to be hoped for. Yet muſt not the Prince for all this abandon the care of Truth, Unity, and Peace: neither of which could poſſibly be provided for by him, without a Coercive Power. For, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing hath a greater influence upon the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Happineſs, and Peace of a Kingdom, then Religion. And that in a double re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect.</p>
            <p>Firſt, In reſpect of the Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which hath promiſed to reward Piety, or Religion, not onely with the great things of Eternity, but with the good things of this preſent life. <hi>Godlineſs</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.8.) <hi>is profitable to all things, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving promiſe of the life that now is, and of that which is to come.</hi> And thus <hi>Livy; Omnia proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra eveniunt colentibus Deos, adverſa ſpernenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus:</hi> that is, All things ſucceed proſperouſly to thoſe, that Worſhip the Gods, but nothing well to thoſe, that deſpiſe them. And <hi>Horace</hi>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:47534:42"/>aſcribes all the miſeries, and calamities, that befel <hi>Italy,</hi> to their neglect of the Gods;
<q>
                  <l>Dii multa, neglecti, dederunt</l>
                  <l>Heſperiae mala luctuoſae.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And it is no wonder (ſaith <hi>Vat. Max.</hi>) that the Gods watch over the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire with a moſt indulgent care; ſeeing the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> are ſo ſcrupulous, in examining, and obſerving the ſmalleſt matters in Religion. <hi>(Quod tam ſcrupuloſa cura parvula quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que momenta religionis examinare videre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, In reſpect of the Nature, the Genuine, and proper Tendency of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which is to render men Peaceable, Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequious, Lovers of their Country, and Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious of the Common welfare. Now, where men are generally thus ſpirited, that State, or Kingdom, muſt needs be flouriſhing, and happy. Thus <hi>Plato</hi> makes Religion <hi>(Legum, &amp; honeſtae vitae vinculum)</hi> the bond of Laws, and all good life; and <hi>Cicero, (Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manae ſocietatis fundamentum)</hi> the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all Humane Society. I ſhall add onely to this, that ſuch a Coercive Power is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to reſtrain that curioſity, and itch of Novelty, that is in men.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:47534:42"/>
All mutation in Religion (though but in the Rites, and Ceremonies of it) if it be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Authori<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ty, or conſent of the Prince, breeds an Earth-quake in the Bowels of the Common-Wealth, and brings it many times into utmoſt danger. Hence the great Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of <hi>Nice</hi> cryed out ſo Paſſionately, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Let the old Cuſtomes take place. But, without a coercive Power in the Prince, this cannot be: for there is in every man a Natural affection of novelty. As they in Ezekiel, <hi>who did ſet their poſts by God's poſts, and their threſholds by his threſholds.</hi> (<hi>Ezek.</hi> 43.8.) ſo men will be bringing a <hi>Baſon,</hi> inſtead of the <hi>Font;</hi> a new <hi>Directory,</hi> inſtead of the old <hi>Liturgy:</hi> unleſs their curioſity by the Prince's Edicts be conſtrained. And thus the Common-Wealth, or Kingdom, will be caſt into a quoti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dian Feaver, or Palſy-fit. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this with that rational ſaying of <hi>Pariſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſis; Licitum eſt principi, abuſum gladii Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualis repellere, eo modo quo poteſt, etiam per gladium materialem: aliter enim gladium ſine cauſa portat.</hi> (<hi>De pot. Regis, &amp; Papae,</hi> c. 21.) It is lawfull for the Prince to repel the abuſe of the Spiritual Sword, in ſuch a way as he beſt can, yea by taking into his hand the material Sword: for otherwiſe he ſhould bear the Sword in vain.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:47534:43"/>
But in what caſes hath the Prince a Coer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cive Power? and how far doth it extend?</p>
            <p>Firſt, He hath a coercive power, not onely in the grand caſes of Blaſphemy, and Hereſy but in thoſe leſſer occaſions of Errour, and Schiſm: he is entruſted with Power to quench the leaſt ſpark, as well as the devouring flame, <hi>Arius</hi> in <hi>Alexandria</hi> was but a little ſpark in the beginning, but, becauſe the Chriſtian Emperour did not timely interpoſe his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority for the quenching it, <hi>(Totum or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bem ejus flamma depopulata eſt)</hi> it became a flame, which conſumed (almoſt) the whole Chriſtian World.</p>
            <p>The Prince's Authority may (and ought to) be exerciſed, in reſtraining dangerous Diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations concerning Religion. <hi>Sozomen</hi> (<hi>l.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 12.) tells us, that <hi>Conſtantine</hi> enacted a Law againſt Diſputes of the Trinity: <hi>(Nemo Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricorum de ſumma Trinitate diſputet)</hi> And <hi>Marcianus</hi> prohibited all Diſputes <hi>(De fide Christiana)</hi> of the Chriſtian Religion. <hi>Andronicus</hi> the Emperour, when his Biſhops were diſputing curiouſly, and ſubtilely, of thoſe words of <hi>Chriſt, (Pater major me eſt) My Father is greater then I;</hi> threatned to caſt them into the River, <hi>(Ni tam periculoſis ſermonibus abſtinerent)</hi> unleſs they did for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear ſuch dangerous Diſcourſes. That of
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:47534:43"/>
               <hi>Siſinius</hi> to <hi>Theodoſius</hi> being moſt true, <hi>(Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putando de ſacris accendi tantum contentiones)</hi> that Contentions only are foſtered by Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations.</p>
            <p>Secondly, To the ſecond Queſtion, How far the Coercive Power of the Prince ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends? It is acknowledged, that his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity may extend to Impriſonment, Confiſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Goods, and Baniſhment of perſons ſinning againſt his Commands: but, whether it may extend to Life, is not ſo manifeſt; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Apoſtle ſaith onely, <hi>Haereticum ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minem devita</hi> (<hi>Titus</hi> 3.10.) The <hi>Gloſs</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Gratian</hi> turns the <hi>Verb</hi> into a <hi>Subſtantive; de vita,</hi> and adds, <hi>ſupple, Tolle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is not (as a learned Gentleman of our Church, in His <hi>Hiſtorical Vindication,</hi> hath obſerved) any example in Hiſtory, of proſecuting an Heretick further, then to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void him; till after God, having given peace to his people, under Chriſtian Emperours; they finding, that, if the Church were in trouble, the State was ſeldom otherwiſe, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided by Laws to puniſh Hereticks. The Councel of <hi>Nice</hi> therefore having, in the year 325, cenſured the opinion of <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> for Heretical, the Emperour (who had formerly granted certain conſiderable Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges to Chriſtians) declared in the year
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:47534:44"/>following (<hi>Haereticos, atque Schiſmaticos, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> privilegiis alienos</hi>) that no Heretick, or Sch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmatick, ſhould have any part in thoſe Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges, but they rarely proceeded to blood unleſs (perhaps) againſt ſome ſeditious Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. And the Holy men of thoſe times uſed earneſt perſwaſions, to deterr men, inclining to that ſeverity, from it; as not eſteeming it to agree with that entire Charity, that ſhould be in Chriſtians. St. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> profeſſeth, he had rather be himſelf ſlain by them, then, by detect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> be any cauſe they ſhould un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo the puniſhment of death. (<hi>Ep.</hi> 127) This was the Temper of the Chriſtians, at leaſt 800. years after <hi>Chriſt.</hi> But about the year 1000, the Chriſtian World began to puniſh Miſcreants <hi>(as branches not bearing fruit in Chriſt)</hi> by caſting them into the fire. But the Devout men of thoſe Times did not approve of this rigour. St. <hi>Bernard,</hi> explaining thoſe words of <hi>Solomon, Take us the Foxes, the little Foxes, that ſpoil the Vines</hi> (<hi>Cant.</hi> 2.15.) If (ſaith he) according to the Allegory, by the Vines we underſtand the Churches, and by the Foxes Hereſies, or rather Hereticks; the meaning is plain, that Hereticks be rather taken, then driven away <hi>(Capientur, dico, non armis, ſed agrumentis)</hi> taken, I ſay, not by Arms, but Arguments, whereby their Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:47534:44"/>may be refuted, and they themſelves reconciled (if poſsible) to the Catholick Church. And that the Holy Ghoſt intends this, is evident (ſaith he) becauſe he doth not ſay ſimply, <hi>Take the Foxes</hi> (ſed capite nobis) <hi>take us the Foxes: ſibi ergo, &amp; ſponſae ſuae, id eſt Catholicae, jubet acquiri has vulpes, cum ait ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pite eas nobis</hi> (<hi>In Cantic. Serm.</hi> 64.) He commands therefore, that they be taken for himſelf, and his Spouſe, that is the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church, when he ſaith, <hi>Take us the Foxes,</hi> Thus the holy men, in that Age, in which they firſt ſtopped mens mouths, not with Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but Arms, judged of it. And indeed we have not many Examples of perſons, ſuffering meerly for Conſcience, till after the year 1216. in which <hi>Pope Innocent the Third</hi> laid the foundation of that new Court, called ſince the <hi>Inquiſition;</hi> who appointed ſuch, as ſhould be convicted of Hereſie <hi>(ut vivi in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectu hominum comburentur)</hi> to be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted alive to the flames of fire.</p>
            <p>And though ſuch proceedings are not at any good agreement with thoſe rules, and examples, which Chriſt hath left us in holy Scripture: yet the practiſe hath been long ſince taken up in this Kingdom, and is in force at this day by the Laws.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno</hi> 1166. about thirty <hi>Dutch</hi> came hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:47534:45"/>who deteſted Baptiſm, the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> and other parts of Religion: and being by Scripture convicted in an Epiſcopal Councel (called by the King at <hi>Oxford</hi>) they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to be Whipped, and burnt in the face, and a command given, that none ſhould ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther receive, or releive them, ſo that they miſerably Periſhed.</p>
            <p>By the Common-Law (that is, the Cuſtom of the Realm) of <hi>England,</hi> Hereticks are to be Puniſhed by Conſuming them with Fire: and (accordingly) there is a Writ <hi>De Haeretico comburendo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Apoſtate Deacon, in a Councel held at <hi>Oxford</hi> (by <hi>Stephen Langton</hi>) was firſt degra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and then (by Lay-hands) committed to the Fire. (<hi>Bracto,</hi> l. 3. <hi>de Corona,</hi> c. 9)</p>
            <p>In <hi>Edward</hi> the Third's daies (about the Year 1347.) two <hi>Franciſcans</hi> were Burnt, <hi>quod de Religione male ſentirent:</hi> becauſe they thought amiſs of Religion. (<hi>Pol. Virg. Hiſt. Ang.</hi> l. 19.)</p>
            <p>And in the year 1583. <hi>Copin</hi> and <hi>Thacker</hi> were hanged (at Saint <hi>Edmonds-Bury</hi>) for publiſhing <hi>Brown</hi>'s Book <hi>(Cambd.) which</hi> (ſaith <hi>Stow,</hi> p. 1174) <hi>was written againſt the Common-Prayer Book. (A Fair warning!)</hi> And thus you ſee, if men will not be Subject to the Higher Powers, in matters of Religion
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:47534:45"/>
               <hi>for Conſcience ſake,</hi> they muſt be ſubject <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of wrath:</hi> for the Prince is entruſted with a Coercive Power, and bears not the Sword in vain.</p>
            <p>But becauſe it is a thing Morally impoſsible, for one man (as the King) to Govern the whole Church in his Kingdom, Perſonally, by himſelf: He may ſubſtitute, or delegate o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers under him, to manage all his Power (which is communicable) in the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church. I ſay <hi>[communicable]</hi> becauſe there are ſome things inſeparable from the Supreme Power, as to Correct, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Ratifie, Repeal, or Make Null Canons, and Conſtitutions, made by any perſons un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him; to reverſe, or mitigate a Sentence injuſtly, or unduly paſſed; the right of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals; of nominating Biſhops to their reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Sees; of tranſlating, or depoſing them, where he ſeeth cauſe. Theſe, and ſuch like, are incommunicable unto any, inſeparable from his Crown. But in all other things, that are not of this nature, he may give Power to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to Govern the Church, to whom all perſons ow their obedience, by virtue of his Delegation, as much as to the King himſelf; becauſe it is the King, that requires, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids any thing by them. Thus St. <hi>Peter</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires Chriſtians to pay their obedience un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:47534:46"/>Governours ſent by him, as well as to the King (the Supreme Power) <hi>Submit your ſelves to every Ordinance of man, for the Lord's ſake: whether it be to the King, as Supreme, or unto Governours, as unto them, that are ſent by him, for the puniſhment of evil-doers, and for the praiſe of them, that do well.</hi> (1 Pet. 2.13, 14.)</p>
            <p>The Governours ſent by the King in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Affairs are the <hi>Reverend Biſhops.</hi> I take the word <hi>Biſhop,</hi> not in the Common and General notion; as every Paſtour, or Presbyter, is a Biſhop: as he doth (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) overſee the particular Flock, commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his charge. Thus the Municipal <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diles,</hi> among the <hi>Romans,</hi> were ſtiled Biſhops: and <hi>Cicero (Campanae orae Epiſcopum ſe dicit constitutum)</hi> was Biſhop of the <hi>Campanian</hi> Territory. But, (in a more proper, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar ſence) for perſons, who have not onely the over-ſight of the Flock, but even of the Paſtours themſelves, a diſtinct Function, and Dignity from <hi>Presbyters,</hi> as the Fathers, and Councels generally understand the word <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop.</hi> Now concerning theſe I affirm,</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> (that is the Prelacy, or Preheminence of one Paſtour among the reſt) is not repugnant to the Scriptures. If I e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince this, that ſaying of <hi>Chriſt, He, that is not againſt us, is on our part</hi> (Mark 9.40.)
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:47534:46"/>will contribute not a little to the confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Order. And, if any man ſhall ſay, that this Order is repugnant to the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture (that is, if he preſume to condemn the whole Chriſtian Church, for more then 1000 years after <hi>Chriſt,</hi> of impiety, or fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) he muſt neceſſarily take upon him the heavy (that I ſay not, intolerable) burthen of making it good.</p>
            <p>There is not (that I am conſcious of) one Text of Scripture, that affords any counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to that opinion, unleſs that in St. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew; Jeſus called them</hi> (the ten Apoſtles) <hi>unto him, and ſaid, Ye know, that the Princes of the Gentiles exerciſe Dominion over them, and they, that are Great, exerciſe Authority upon them: But it ſhall not be ſo among you:</hi> (Mat. 20.25, 26.) And ſomewhat more to their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) in the tenth of St. <hi>Mark,</hi> 44. <hi>Whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever of you will be chiefest, ſhall be the ſervant of all.</hi> To theſe Texts I Anſwer,
<list>
                  <item>1. The <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> (of old) and other Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natick ſpirits, ſuppoſing the <hi>Antitheſis</hi> here to be between the Gentiles, and the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an State, have extended the Pronoun [<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>] <hi>among you,</hi> to the whole Goſpel-Church, and all Chriſtians in it. And from thence they conclude, that <hi>It is unlawfull for Chriſtians to exerciſe any Rule, or Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:47534:47"/>over their Brethren.</hi> So that the ſame Text, by which ſome would caſt Epiſcopacy out of the Church, is made uſe of by others (to as good purpoſe) to thruſt Magiſtracy out of the Chriſtian World.</item>
                  <item>2. Some Learned Interpreters (weighing the expreſſion uſed by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>] <hi>in eas dominari,</hi> they Lord it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them (<hi>Id eſt, cum quadam acerbitate;</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za) with bitterneſs, and rigour) underſtand <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s prohibition of an unjuſt, and Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannical Power onely: ſuch as the Princes of the Gentiles generally uſed over thoſe, that were ſubject to them. And ſo <hi>Chriſt</hi> doth not dehort his Apoſtles from exerciſing Power, and Authority over their Brethren, but onely from the Tyrannical abuſe of Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</item>
                  <item>3. The <hi>Presbyterians</hi> themſelves (in fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Parts) do generally acknowledg, that this Text (in St. <hi>Matt.</hi>) doth not take away the Eccleſiaſtical Authority of Teaching, Bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Looſing, according to the Goſpel, <hi>vel gradus Eccleſiaſticorum, a Chriſto inſtitutes, &amp; datos Eccleſiae;</hi> no, nor thoſe degrees of Eccleſiaſtical Perſons, that were inſtituted, and appointed his Church by Chriſt; <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, Prophets, Teachers,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>(Paraeus)</hi> he intends not by that Prohibition (in St. <hi>Matt.</hi>)
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:47534:47"/>to bring a Parity, or Equality into the Church: <hi>Nam ſic tolleretur omnis ordo, inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heretur confuſio</hi> (as He) for ſo all Order would be aboliſhed, and Confuſion introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the room of it.</item>
                  <item>4. The deſign, and intent of <hi>Chriſt</hi> (in the forementioned Text) is not to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all Preheminence, or Primacy among the Apoſtles, or Paſtours of the Church; but to admoniſh the Apoſtles (and enſuing Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours) of the Church; that their High, and Honourable Calling, hath the Miniſtry, or Service of the Church, annexed to it. Now this is ſo far from being inconſiſtent with Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence, and Authority, that even Kings themſelves ſerve the Church, and Kingdom, in their High Calling. So King <hi>Antigonus</hi> to his Son; <hi>An ignoras, fili mi, nostrum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnum nobilem eſſe ſervitutem?</hi> 
                     <q>Art thou ignorant, O my Son, that our Empire is nothing elſe, but a more noble ſervitude.</q> Though therefore the Apoſtles, and their Succeſſours, are required to be Miniſters, and Servants to all; this doth not take away their Preheminence any more, then a Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard's ſerving his Flock, or a Tutour's ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his Pupil, or the King's ſerving his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, takes away the Reſpective Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or Preheminence of the Shepheard, Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:47534:48"/>or King, over thoſe, whom they ſerve.</item>
                  <item>5. This Text is ſo far from aboliſhing Prelacy, and Preheminence, among the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and Paſtours, that it confirms, and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſheth it. For, when St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> and St. <hi>Mark</hi> ſay, He <hi>that will be greateſt</hi> among you; St. <hi>Luke</hi> ſaith, [he <hi>that is</hi> greateſt] and [he <hi>that is</hi> chief] <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.26. and you may obſerve, that our Lord <hi>Chriſt</hi> propounds his own example, as a pattern to them, <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever will be Chief among you, let him be your Servant; even as the Son of Man came not to be Miniſtred unto, but to Miniſter.</hi> (Mat. 20.27, 28.) The Duty therefore of Miniſtring to, or ſerving others, doth not hinder; but that he, who Miniſters, or ſerves, may be Greater, then thoſe, to whom he Miniſters: unleſs, by urging this Text for a Parity among Paſtours, they intend to level (the great A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle) <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf, to be no more, then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual to the other Apoſtles. And one would wonder (did not Prejudice, and Intereſt draw a Film over the eye of mens Reaſon) how any man could entertain a thought, that ever <hi>Chriſt</hi> intended a Parity among Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Perſons, when, by his own finger from Heaven, he hath ſo evidently pointed out a diſparity among them. He gave ſome <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and ſome <hi>Prophets;</hi> and ſome <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſts;</hi>
                     <pb n="119" facs="tcp:47534:48"/>and ſome <hi>Paſtours,</hi> and <hi>Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers:</hi> (<hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11.) which are not onely diſtinct Functions in the Church, but diſtinct Degrees; as is evident by the Apoſtle, in the firſt to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> 12.28. And God hath ſet ſome in the Church, <hi>firſt</hi> Apoſtles, <hi>ſecondarily</hi> Prophets, <hi>thirdly</hi> Teachers, <hi>after that</hi> Miracles, <hi>then</hi> Gifts of Healings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The Evangeliſts themſelves are (as <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nom.</hi> ad <hi>Fabiol.) Secundi ordinis, &amp; minoris gradus;</hi> but of a ſecond Order, and inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our degree, (<hi>Dignitate minores Apoſtolis,</hi> as <hi>Calvin</hi>) inferiour to the Apoſtles in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnity. The firſt Aſſertion then (namely, <hi>That Epiſcopacy, that is the Prelacy, or Prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence of one Pastour among the reſt, is not repugnant to the Scriptures,</hi>) is undeniably true.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Church Catholick (that is, the Congregation of <hi>Christians</hi> in all the World,) hath received, and embraced the Epiſcopacy we contend for. To this all the Fathers (without exception of any one) bear witneſs. He among them, who aſcribes leaſt to Epiſcopacy, St. <hi>Jerom,</hi> who was not a Biſhop, but a <hi>Presbyter</hi> of an inferiour Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der (whoſe Teſtimony therefore may ſtand in ſtead of many) ſaith, <hi>In toto orbe decretum est, ut unus, de Presbyteris electus, caeteris ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perponeretur:
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:47534:49"/>ad quem omnis cura Eccleſiae pertineret.</hi> It is univerſally decreed, that <hi>one,</hi> choſen from among the <hi>Presbyters,</hi> ſhould be ſet over the reſt, to whom the whole care of the Church ſhould appertain. And that this was the univerſal Cuſtom of the Church, appears by this, becauſe thoſe Hereticks, who made a ſeparation from the Church Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, did yet retain this Order among them. Thus the Authour of the <hi>Homilies</hi> upon St. <hi>Matthew. Hereticks, in their Schiſm, have all thoſe things among them, which are proper to the true Church. (Similiter Eccleſias, ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Scripturas, ſimiliter Epiſcopos, caeterosque Clericorum ordines.) They have their Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, Scriptures, Biſhops, and other Orders of the Clergy, as the Church hath. Aerius</hi> indeed (in a Pang of indignation, becauſe he miſſed a Biſhoprick, which he ſtood for) would have made himſelf equal to the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Biſhops, by broaching this Doctrine <hi>(Presbyterum ab Epiſcopo nulla differentia diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerni debere.)</hi> That a <hi>Presbyter</hi> ought not to be diſtinguiſhed by any difference from a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop; but this errour of his was condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the whole Church. When one wrote to St. <hi>Jerom, (Nihil intereſt inter Epiſcopum &amp; Presbyterum.)</hi> There is no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a Biſhop, and a <hi>Presbyter:</hi> he repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:47534:49"/>him ſharply in the Anſwer, which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned <hi>(Hoc ſatis imperite)</hi> This was not ſaid for want of ignorance <hi>(In portu, ut dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, naufragium)</hi> you make ſhipwrack (as they ſay Proverbially) in the Haven.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The Epiſcopacy under our preſent conſideration, is of venerable Antiquity in the Church: having it's riſe in the Apoſtles time. In proof of which, we can have no better E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, then the Catalogue of Biſhops in <hi>Irenaeus, Euſebius, Socrates,</hi> and <hi>Theodoret;</hi> who begin from the Age, in which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles lived. Now no man can deny his aſſent to ſuch Grave Authority, ſo unanimouſly conſpiring in matter of fact, without incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the guilt of ſingular irreverence, and pertinacy. It is, as if one ſhould deny (that, which all the <hi>Roman</hi> Hiſtories affirm) that the Conſulſhip of <hi>Rome</hi> began from the Baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Tarquins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Will you hear St. <hi>Jerom? Alexandriae, a Marco Evangeliſta, Presbyteri unum ſemper, ex ſe electum, in celſiori gradu collocatum, Epiſcopum nominabant.</hi> (Ep. 85.) The <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> ever ſince St. <hi>Mark</hi> the Evangeliſt, having choſen one from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves, and exalting him to an high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er place, ſtiled him Biſhop.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Mark</hi> died in the eighth year of <hi>Nero,</hi>
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:47534:50"/>about the year of our Lord 62. whoſe Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour (St. <hi>John</hi> the Apoſtle yet living) was <hi>Amianus;</hi> to him ſucceeded <hi>Abilius;</hi> to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilius, Cerdo.</hi> After the Death of St. <hi>James, Simon</hi> ſucceeded him, in the Biſhoprick of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> After St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s departure <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Anacletus,</hi> and <hi>Clement;</hi> or (as ſome) St. <hi>Peter</hi> yet living, ſate in the Epiſcopal Chair at <hi>Rome:</hi> as <hi>Evodius,</hi> and <hi>Ignatius</hi> did at <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch.</hi> A Record of ſuch Antiquity, confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by <hi>Ignatius,</hi> the Diſciple of St. <hi>John,</hi> cannot be rejected by any, ſave ſuch onely, who have no Faith for any thing, that them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſaw not. Who may as well deny, that ever there was a <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> or <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> or <hi>Henry</hi> King of <hi>England;</hi> as that the perſons, before mentioned, were Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of their reſpective Sees.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The Epiſcopacy we intend, is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by Divine Right, or (as <hi>Bucer</hi> expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it) <hi>Viſum Spiritui Sancto, utinter Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teros unus cur am ſingularem gereret.</hi> It ſeemed good unto the Holy Ghoſt, that one among the <hi>Presbyters</hi> ſhould have the eſpecial care of the Church. Of this we have an undenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Argument, in the book of the <hi>Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons:</hi> where we find <hi>Chriſt</hi> from Heaven commanding St. <hi>John</hi> to write unto the ſeven Angels of the Churches of <hi>Aſia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:47534:50"/>
The Title of <hi>Angel</hi> may, I acknowledg, be applyed (in a general ſignification) to every particular Paſtour, or <hi>Presbyter.</hi> But here it is manifeſt <hi>Chriſt</hi> intends one, in each Church onely: whom he ſtiles the Angel, in a proper, and peculiar ſence. For, It is no ways probable, that Churches ſo large, of ſuch vaſt extent, as <hi>Epheſus, Smyrna,</hi> and the reſt were, had but one Paſtour, or <hi>Presbyter,</hi> in each of them. Nay, it is certain, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident, concerning <hi>Epheſus,</hi> that in the days of St <hi>Paul,</hi> there were many <hi>Presbyters</hi> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, or conſtituted to feed the Church of God. <hi>Acts</hi> 20.17. <hi>And from Miletus he ſent to Epheſus, and called the Elders of the Church, and ſaid unto them</hi> (verſe 28.) <hi>Take heed unto your ſelves, and to all the flock,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>to feed the Church of God.</hi> And we may as rationally conclude, concerning the reſt, that there were many Paſtours in each Church. Why then ſhould <hi>Christ</hi> direct his Epiſtle to one, <hi>[the Angel]</hi> if there had not been one among them of a Superiour Function, and more eminent Dignity? <hi>Sub Angeli no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> Epiſt. 162.) <hi>lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datur praepoſitus Eccleſiae;</hi> Under the name of the <hi>Angel</hi> he commends the Prefect of the Church. <hi>Angelos, Eccleſiis Praeſidentes di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xit: (Hierom)</hi> By <hi>Angels,</hi> he underſtands
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:47534:51"/>the Preſidents of the Churches. And for <hi>Smyrna, Polycarpus</hi> was (without contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie) Biſhop of it, ordained by St. <hi>John</hi> (as <hi>Bullinger</hi> himſelf acknowledgeth)and <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renaeus</hi> ſaith of him (<hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 3.) <hi>Polycarpus non ſolum ab Apoſtolis eruditus,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Polycarp</hi> was not onely inſtructed by the Apoſtles, and converſant with divers of thoſe perſons, who ſaw our Lord in the fleſh; but in <hi>Aſia</hi> he was conſtituted, by the Apoſtles, Biſhop of the Church of <hi>Smyrna,</hi> whom I ſaw (ſaith the <hi>Father</hi>) while I was a young man. I whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wave many other Evidences, and deſcend to a late Proteſtant Writer, <hi>Marlorat (in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum)</hi> St. <hi>John,</hi> ſaith he, mentions firſt the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> in reſpect of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnity of the place; <hi>Nec populum aggreditur, ſed Principem Cleri, utique Epiſcopum.</hi> And he doth not apply himſelf to the people, but to the Principal of the Clergy, to wit, the Biſhop. And becauſe the Authority of Mr. <hi>Beza,</hi> and Doctour <hi>Reinolds,</hi> may poſsibly go furtheſt with thoſe, who have no great friendſhip for the Epiſcopal Dignity, let us (in the Point in hand) hear them. To the Angel (ſaith <hi>Beza</hi>) <hi>id eſt,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Quem nimirum oportuit inprimis de his rebus admone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri, ac per eum caeteros collegas, totamque adeo Eccleſiam.</hi> That is the Preſident, who firſt
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:47534:51"/>ought to be admoniſhed, and by him his Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leagues, and ſo the whole Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reinolds,</hi> in his Conference with <hi>Hart</hi> (<hi>c.</hi> 8. <hi>Sect.</hi> 3.) ſaith. <hi>Though there were in the Church of Epheſus many Presbyters, and Paſtours, to Adminiſter to that Church, yet there was one ever thoſe many, whom our Saviour ſtiles the Angel of the Church, to whom he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects thoſe things, which he would have the reſt to learn from him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, the moſt antient <hi>Greek</hi> Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripts of the New Teſtament, in the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the ſecond Epiſtle to <hi>Timothy,</hi> have theſe words <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. The ſecond Epiſtle to <hi>Timothy, erdained the firſt Biſhop of the Church of the Epheſians,</hi> &amp;c. And in the end of the Epiſtle to <hi>Titus,</hi> we tranſlate from the ſame Manuſcripts, It was written to <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, ordained the firſt Biſhop of the Church of the Cretians.</hi> And St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> tells us, that <hi>Evedius</hi> (his Predeceſſour) was ordained Biſhop of the <hi>Epheſians, by the Apoſtles</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.)</p>
            <p>I will add onely to this, that God himſelf (who gave Laws in mediately to the people of the <hi>Jews</hi>) conſtituted, and appointed an High-Prieſt, upon whom he conferred Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy, and Preheminence, over the reſt of the
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:47534:52"/>Prieſts. And if any man object, that the High-Prieſt was a Type of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg it is true. But the entire Inſtitution of his Office was not for that end onely, his Eminence was conferred upon him for Order ſake in the Church. As Kingly Government, was (in a ſort) Typical of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was not onely Typical of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but Inſtituted likewiſe for the great ends of Government, it may, and ought to be retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: and ſo Prelacy among Paſtours, condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing ſo much, as it doth, to Order in the Church, ought not to be aboliſhed, though it were Typical in the High-Prieſt.</p>
            <p>Thus you have an account of theſe Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours in the Church (the Reverend Biſhops) <hi>ſent by the King;</hi> I mean, in reſpect of the External, and Accidental things of Religion: they have another Miſsion, even from the Holy Ghoſt, in reſpect of the Internal Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Adminiſtring Sacraments, Ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Binding and Looſing, and ſuch like. Since then Prelacy is not contrary to the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, ſince the Church Catholick hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and embraced it, ſince it is of very Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Antiquity, and approved of by Divine Right; this one would think, ſhould be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to prepare a room for it in the heart of any pious, and ſober Chriſtian; enough
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:47534:52"/>to beget in us a reverent eſteem of the calling of Biſhops, to work in us a chearfull ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to, and ready compliance with the Rites, and Ceremonies in the Worſhip of God, commended to, and required of us, by ſuch perſons, delegated to that end by the Prince, whoſe Authority, in matters of Religion, hath ſufficiently been aſſerted.</p>
            <p>I will yet add (for the better reconciling this Order to the affections of ſome men) two words.</p>
            <p n="1">I. The Conveniency, and Expediency (that, I ſay not, Neceſsity) of Conformity, and Agreement, between the Eccleſiaſtical, and Civil Government. There is ſuch an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finity between theſe two, that in Common-Wealths, where the Government is by many, they always commend the Affairs of the Church to the Clergy, or <hi>Presbytery,</hi> and not to a Biſhop: but where the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is Monarchical in the State, Epiſcopacy in the Church is onely conformable to it; <hi>Presbytery</hi> no way comporting with Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy. Hence that <hi>Preverbial</hi> ſaying, <hi>No Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, No King.</hi> A ſaying that may be eaſily derided, but not ſo eaſily refuted. Our late ſad Experiences have engraven it in ſuch Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital Characters upon the underſtandings of all ſober, and unprejudiced perſons, than it will not eaſily be defaced.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:47534:53"/>
II. The Utility, and Advantages, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound to the Church by Epiſcopacy. I might entertain you (upon this Head) with the unanimous conſent of all Hiſtorians, but I ſelect his Teſtimony onely, who, of all the Antients, had the leaſt affection for Biſhops. St. <hi>Jerom</hi> (ad Tit. c. 1.) <hi>Toto orbe decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt, ut ad tollenda ſchiſmata, &amp; diſſidia, unus, de Presbyteris electus, ſuperponeretur cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teris.</hi> It is universally decreed, that, for the prevention of Schiſms, and differences, one choſen out of the <hi>Presbyters,</hi> be ſet over the reſt. And again; <hi>Eccleſiae ſalus in ſummi ſacerdotis, id eſt, Epiſcopi, dignitate conſiſtit;</hi> The ſafety of the Church conſiſts in the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnity of the High-Prieſt, that is, the Biſhop: to whom, if there be not a Peculiar Power, diſtinct from all others, annexed; <hi>Tot in Eccleſia efficientur ſchiſmata, quot ſacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> (adverſ. <hi>Lucif.</hi>) There will be as many Schiſms, as Prieſts in the Church.</p>
            <p>Our own Chronicles tell us, that King <hi>Edward</hi> the Elder, by Conſtituting five new Biſhops, ſtopped an Inundation of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganiſm, ready to break in on the Weſt, for want of Paſtours.</p>
            <p>If any man queſtion, or doubt of the Utility of this Reverend Order, let him look back upon the Torrent of Confuſion, Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:47534:53"/>and Blaſphemy, that brake in upon us, while theſe Banks were by violent hands thrown down. <hi>Hoc</hi> Ithacus <hi>velit,</hi> &amp;c. The Extirpation of <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> in theſe Kingdoms is the <hi>firſt-born</hi> of the <hi>Pope</hi>'s deſires; That, which his Soul longs for, as for the <hi>firſt-ripe fruit;</hi> you know the <hi>Apologue,</hi> how the <hi>Wolves</hi> would make peace with the <hi>Sheep,</hi> upon the condition, they would hang up all their <hi>dogs.</hi> Let but <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> and the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy,</hi> be aboliſhed, and the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> aſſure you, ſhall promiſe you <hi>peace</hi> upon any terms.</p>
            <p>There is nothing (that I know of) <hi>objected</hi> againſt this <hi>Order,</hi> but (that great <hi>Bug-bear</hi>) the <hi>Covenant. Have we not lifted up our hands to the God of Heaven, and</hi> ſworn <hi>the Extirpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Prelacy? How then can we admit of</hi> Biſhops, <hi>or ſubmit to them, being reſtored?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I <hi>Anſwer;</hi> An <hi>unlawfull Oath</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligeth to nothing, but <hi>repentance.</hi> An <hi>unjuſt Oath,</hi> voluntarily taken, or impoſed by an unlawfull Authority, is not binding to any man's Conſcience.</p>
            <p>You have Covenanted, and ſworn the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpation of Prelacy:</hi> ſo did <hi>Herod</hi> binde him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <hi>with an oath</hi> to <hi>Herodias</hi> Daughter, that he would give her whatſoever ſhe ſhould ask; <hi>Matthew</hi> xiv. 7. ſo did certain <hi>Jews</hi> binde themſelves with an <hi>Oath of Execration, that
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:47534:54"/>they would neither eat, nor drink, till they had killed</hi> Paul; <hi>Acts</hi> xxiii. 12. Had thoſe men done well in killing <hi>Paul;</hi> becauſe they had bound themſelves by a <hi>curſe?</hi> or did <hi>Herod</hi> well, in giving <hi>John Bapriſt</hi>'s Head to the <hi>Damſel,</hi> for his <hi>Oath</hi>'s <hi>ſake?</hi> you will (I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume) ſay, <hi>No.</hi> Why <hi>No?</hi> would you not have them keep their <hi>Oath?</hi> I; but it was an <hi>unjuſt Oath.</hi> So was yours, and will be found <hi>defective</hi> in the Properties, required in a <hi>juſt</hi> Oath, <hi>Truth, Judgment,</hi> and <hi>Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> (<hi>Jer.</hi> iv. 2.) And we may ſoberly ſuppoſe, that many men Covenanted againſt the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops,</hi> for their Land's ſake onely. As the Earl of <hi>Kildare,</hi> being Arraigned for burning a Church in <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſaid, He would never have ſet fire to the Church, if he had not thought the <hi>Biſhop</hi> had been in it. Bur, if any man can ſay, He took the <hi>Covenant,</hi> in <hi>Truth, Judgment,</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> he might lie under ſome temptation or keeping it, had it not wanted (that, which is <hi>eſſentially</hi> neceſſary to render an Oath <hi>obliging</hi>) a lawfull Authority to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it. But, ſeeing it wanted this, (which it were Treaſon to deny) no man's Conſcience is obliged by it: and he, who will perſiſt in it becauſe he hath <hi>taken</hi> it, juſtifies his doing of <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil,</hi> by doing of <hi>worſe.</hi> Since therefore through the goodneſs of <hi>God,</hi> and his <hi>Majeſtie</hi>'s un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:47534:54"/>Reſolution) the Reverend <hi>Biſhops</hi> are reſtored to the <hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>ſent as Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours by the King:</hi> if you be <hi>Members</hi> of this <hi>Spiritual Houſe,</hi> you muſt ſubmit to their <hi>Directions,</hi> and <hi>Injunctions,</hi> in all <hi>Rites, Ceremonies,</hi> and <hi>Circumſtances</hi> of Religion. Which fairly leads me to (the laſt thing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended) the <hi>Conſideration,</hi> and <hi>Vindication of the</hi> Liturgy <hi>of our Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Calves of our lips</hi> (our <hi>Prayers</hi>) are a <hi>ſervice</hi> more acceptable to the God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, then <hi>Hecatombs</hi> of <hi>Oxen,</hi> Thouſands of <hi>Rams,</hi> or ten Thouſand Rivers of <hi>Oyl.</hi> An <hi>Heathen</hi> could ſay, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Prayers are a more acceptable Sacrifice to God, then Oxen.</hi> That part of our lives, which we ſpend in <hi>Prayer,</hi> is the moſt celeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and Divine. <hi>Prayer</hi> is a <hi>Duty</hi> ſo abſolutely neceſſary for every perſon, who acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a <hi>Deitie,</hi> that <hi>Nature</hi> hath dictated it to thoſe, who were ſtrangers to the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and <hi>Aliens to the Common-Wealth of</hi> Iſrael. The <hi>Mariners</hi> (in <hi>Jonah</hi>) when the Storm was up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on them, <hi>cryed, every man, unto his God;</hi> (Chap. i. verſe 5.) and the <hi>Mr. of the Ship</hi> rebuked the <hi>Prophet</hi> himſelf ſharply for neglecting this <hi>Duty,</hi> with <hi>What meaneſt thou, O Sleeper? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe, call upin thy God;</hi> verſe 6. The <hi>Sun</hi> hath never yet beheld a perſon ſo impudent (pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:47534:55"/>he did not <hi>ſay in his heart</hi> with <hi>David</hi>'s Fool, <hi>There is no God</hi>) as plainly, and direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to condemn this <hi>Duty.</hi> In the exerciſe, or performance of which we are diverſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned: after one manner, as we are men, <hi>private</hi> perſons: and after another, as we are <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and <hi>members</hi> of (this <hi>Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al houſe,</hi> on <hi>family</hi>) the <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As <hi>Private</hi> perſons, we are left free, to make choice of ſuch <hi>Time, Place,</hi> and <hi>Form,</hi> as the Exigence of our preſent occaſions re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſ,</hi> For <hi>Time:</hi> either the <hi>Sixth hour</hi> (as St. <hi>Peter,</hi> in <hi>Acts</hi> x. 9.) or the <hi>Ninth hour</hi> (as the <hi>Centurion,</hi> verſe 3) either <hi>thrice</hi> a day, as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>) <hi>at Evening, Morning, and Noon</hi> (Pſal. lv. 17.) <hi>Or Seaven</hi> times a Day, as He, <hi>Pſal.</hi> cxix. 164.</p>
            <p>Secondly, For <hi>Place:</hi> either in <hi>Cloſet, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper-Room, Garden, Fields,</hi> or elſwhere, with conveniency.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, For the <hi>Manner:</hi> either taking unto our ſelves <hi>words,</hi> and <hi>expreſſions</hi> of our own, or making uſe of apt, and pertinent <hi>Forms</hi> invented by others. In all theſe <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances</hi> we are free, and at our own electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as <hi>private perſons.</hi> But, as we are in <hi>Family, Members</hi> of the <hi>houſe,</hi> a <hi>publick</hi> body, we are not left free, but are under the directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:47534:55"/>on of our <hi>Spiritual guids,</hi> or <hi>Governours,</hi> in all theſe reſpects of <hi>time, place,</hi> and <hi>form.</hi> In then <hi>two</hi> firſt of theſe, <hi>time,</hi> and <hi>place,</hi> all (who are called <hi>Chriſtians</hi>) agree, that the <hi>King,</hi> (or <hi>Governours</hi> under him) may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe, that <hi>publique Prayers</hi> ſhall be made at ſuch <hi>times,</hi> and in ſuch <hi>places</hi> onely. But the <hi>third,</hi> the preſcribing a <hi>Form,</hi> will by no means be allowed by ſome to the <hi>Spiritual Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours,</hi> or any others. And others (who allow the <hi>King,</hi> and thoſe, who are under him, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to preſcribe a <hi>form</hi> of <hi>publique Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi>) wil not admit of that, which we call <hi>The Book of Common Prayer, and Administration of the Sacraments.</hi> I ſhall endeavour there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, firſt, to vindicate <hi>ſet Forms</hi> of <hi>Prayer</hi> in <hi>General;</hi> and, ſecondly, the <hi>Liturgy</hi> of our Church in <hi>Particular.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, For the <hi>lawfulneſs,</hi> and <hi>expediencie</hi> of <hi>ſet Forms</hi> of <hi>Prayer,</hi> I offer four Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>The Example of God himſelf, and of ſome Holy men, who were enſpired by the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt.</hi> In the ſixth <hi>Chapter</hi> of the <hi>Book</hi> of <hi>Numbers,</hi> verſe 22, and foreward, you have a <hi>form</hi> of <hi>Bleſſing the people</hi> preſcribed, by God himſelf, to <hi>Aaron,</hi> and his ſons. <hi>The Lord ſpake unto</hi> Moſes, <hi>ſaying, Speak unto</hi> Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, <hi>and his ſons, ſaying, On this wiſe ye ſhall
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:47534:56"/>bleſs the Children of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>ſaying unto them, The Lord bleſs thee, and keep thee; the Lord make his face ſhine upon thee, and be gracious un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee: the Lord lift up his countenance upon thee, and give thee peace.</hi> And, as God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed the <hi>Prieſts</hi> a <hi>Form</hi> to <hi>Bleſs the people,</hi> ſo he preſcribes the <hi>People</hi> a <hi>Form,</hi> in theſe words; <hi>And thou ſhalt go unto the Prieſt, that ſhall be in thoſe days, and ſay unto him, I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs this day unto the Lord thy God, that I am come unto the Countrey, which the Lord ſware unto our Fathers for to give us</hi> (Deut: xxvi. 3) and (<hi>verſe</hi> 5.) <hi>Thou ſhalt speak, and ſay before the Lord thy God, A</hi> Syrian <hi>ready to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh</hi> was <hi>my Father,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>When they went to <hi>Battel,</hi> a <hi>Form</hi> was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed (<hi>Deut:</hi> xx. 3.) a <hi>form</hi> of <hi>Thanksgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving</hi> for <hi>victory,</hi> and <hi>deliverance. Then ſang</hi> Moſes, <hi>and the Children of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>this Song un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord, and ſpake, ſaying, I will ſing unto the Lord: for he hath triumphed gloriouſly, the Horſe, and his Rider hath He thrown into the Sea,</hi> &amp;c. (Exod. xx. 1.) This Song was composed by <hi>Moſes,</hi> and learned by all the People, and repeated again, in the ſame words, by <hi>Miriam,</hi> (verſe 21.) <hi>And</hi> Miri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am <hi>anſwered them, Sing ye unto the Lord: for</hi> &amp;c. <hi>King</hi> Hezekiah, delivered from Death, did not onely compoſe a <hi>Set-Form</hi> of <hi>Thanksgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving;</hi>
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:47534:56"/>but uſed it all the Daies of his Life. <hi>The Lord was ready to ſave me: therefore we will ſing my Songs to the ſtringed Inſtruments, all the daies of our Life in the Houſe of the Lord.</hi> (Iſa. xxxviii. 20.) And the ſame <hi>Hezekiah</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the <hi>Levites</hi> to ling praiſes to God, <hi>with the words of</hi> David, <hi>and</hi> Aſaph. (2 <hi>Chron.</hi> xxix. 30.) <hi>VVith the Words of</hi> David, and Aſaph; that is, with Forms, compoſed by thoſe Sacred Pen-men.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The <hi>Practiſe,</hi> and <hi>Precept</hi> of our Lord <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> is a ſecond <hi>Argument.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. This <hi>Practiſe</hi> (Matth. xxvi. 44.) <hi>And he left them, and he went again, and prayed the third time, ſaying the ſame words.</hi> And again upon the <hi>Croſs</hi> (Matth. xxvii. 46.) <hi>My God, my God, Why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> The expreſſe words' of <hi>David</hi> (Pſal. xxii. 1.)</p>
            <p n="2">2. VVe have his <hi>Precept</hi> likewiſe, in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing the <hi>Pater Neſter,</hi> not onely as a <hi>Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern,</hi> but <hi>Form</hi> of <hi>Prayer.</hi> For, though he ſay in St. <hi>Matthew, After this manner there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore pray ye, Our Father,</hi> &amp;c. (<hi>Matt.</hi> vi. 9.) yet he ſaith in St. <hi>Luke, When ye pray, ſay, Our Father,</hi> &amp;c. (<hi>Luke</hi> xi. 2.) Since there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Chriſt</hi> (in whom <hi>all the Treaſures of Wiſdom, and Knowledg, were hid,</hi> in whom <hi>the
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:47534:57"/>fulneſs of the Godhead dwelt bodily,</hi> to whom <hi>the Spirit was not given by meaſure</hi> preſcribes, and practiſech a <hi>Form of Prayer;</hi> the <hi>Sons of men</hi> may, without diſparagement to their Parts, or Gifts, lawfully make uſe of a Set-Form.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The Example of St. <hi>John Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt;</hi> who taught his Diſciples to Pray, by preſcribing them a Form (which occaſioned the Diſciples of <hi>Chriſt</hi> to deſire, and him to anſwer their reqneſt, in giving them a Form) <hi>Luke</hi> xi. 1. To which (that excellent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, whoſe loſs the Church could hardly have ſuſtained, had not God, by his Providence, in taking him from us, near the time of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie's happy Reſtauration, ſwallowed up our Sorrows in victory of that Joy) the ever-to-be-Honoured Doctour <hi>Hammond</hi> adds an Apoſtolical Example, from that ſaying of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> in the firſt to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> xiv. 26. <hi>How is it then Brethren? When you come together, every one of you hath a Pſalm. Which</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>refers to ſome of the</hi> Pſalms <hi>of</hi> David, <hi>or</hi> Aſaph; <hi>which were then ordinarily uſed in their devotion: and, becauſe every one had his</hi> ſeveral Pſalm, <hi>it is therefore reproved by the Apoſtle; as a thing tending to confuſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, The Practiſe of the Univerſal
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:47534:57"/>Church. He, who liſts, need not glean after the Reapers; but may fill his Boſom with ſheaves of Teſtimonies, collected by the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent hand of <hi>Caſſander:</hi> and ſince by the late VVriters concerning <hi>Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Greek</hi> Church hath Records of <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgies,</hi> or <hi>ſet Forms of Prayer,</hi> made by St. <hi>James,</hi> contracted by St. <hi>Baſil,</hi> and again ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breviated by St. <hi>Chryſoſtom.</hi> And Hiſtories mention a ſhort <hi>Form</hi> of St. <hi>Peter's;</hi> which alone (they ſay) was uſed in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church for a great while. And we have men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion likewiſe of St. <hi>Mark</hi>'s <hi>Liturgie.</hi> But (though theſe may admit ſome ſcruple, or doubt) St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> (I am ſure) ſpeaks of ſome Forms, retained in the Church, (and ſtill to be found in our Liturgy) particularly that (in the Adminiſtration of the Lord's Supper) of <hi>Surſum corda,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Lift up your hearts.</hi> Of which he ſaith, that they are (<hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba ab ipſis Apoſtolorum temporibus petita</hi>) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsions borrowed from the very times of the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>And for many other particular Forms (uſed by us) we find them in <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> his Catechiſm. <hi>Ignatius</hi> is clear, and expreſs for a Form; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:47534:58"/>(<hi>Ep.</hi> ad <hi>Magneſ.</hi>) Let all meet toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the ſame action (or, place) in Prayer, <hi>Let there be oue Common Prayer,</hi> one minde. And (waving plenteous Inſtances) take one Grand Teſtimony of Set-Forms, in ſtead of many. The <hi>Milevitan Councel,</hi> c. 12. <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euit, ut preces, quae probatae fuerint in Concilio, ab omnibus celebrentur, nec aliae omnino dican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in Eccleſia, niſi quae a prudentioribus tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctantur, vel comprobatae in Synodo fuerint; ne forte aliquid contra fidem, aut per ignoran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam, aut per minus ſtudium, ſit compoſitum.</hi> The Councel thought good, that the Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, which were approved in the Councel, ſhould be uſed by all, and that no other ſhould be ſaid in the Church, but thoſe, that had been weighed by the more prudent, or approved in a Synod; <hi>leſt any thing through ignorance, or neglect, ſhould be done againſt the Faith.</hi> Theſe are ſome Arguments (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong others) for the vindication of <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgies,</hi> or Set-Forms of Prayer in General. I proceed to conſider,</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Compoſition of our <hi>Liturgy</hi> (the <hi>Liturgie</hi> of the Church <hi>England</hi>) and in purſuance of this, I ſhall advance by three ſteps.</p>
            <p n="1">I. The Deriſion, Scorn, and Reproach,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:47534:58"/>which is caſt upon our <hi>Liturgy,</hi> by many, is ſo far from being a ſtumbling-block, or ſtone of offence, to ſcandalize any diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſtian, that it is rather an Argument, evincing the dignity, and excellency of it. For</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The beſt things when they are ſet up as a mark to ſhoot at, by perſons poſſeſſed with diſdain, or diſlike of them, may be cavilled at, and faulted, eaſily ſcorned, and derided. Some <hi>Criticks</hi> have been ſo bold, as to finde fault with the Frame, and order of the great <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick</hi> of the World, and called it (Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, confuſion, or Confuſed mixture, and it is reported of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phenſo</hi> (Surnamed <hi>The Wiſe</hi>) one of the Kings of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> that he uſed many times to ſay, That, if he had ſtod at God's elbow when he made the World, many things ſhould have been ordered better, then they were in die firſt Creation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> We ought not to be Scandalized at our Liturgie in reſpect of the ſcoffs &amp; jears of its adverſaries, becauſe it is no more then the Holy Ghoſt hath foretold concerning theſe times, by the Apoſtles, St <hi>Peter,</hi> and St. <hi>Jude. There ſhall come in the laſt days ſcoffers,</hi> 2 Pet. 3.
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:47534:59"/>
               <hi>There ſhall be Mockers in the laſt time;</hi> (Jude 18.) Though therefore men ſtile it, in deriſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>The</hi> Engliſh <hi>Maſs-Book,</hi> and <hi>The Starve-us-Book,</hi> and what not that is ugly; theſe may argue the Unchriſtianneſs of the perſons, that belch them forth, but they do not evince the Anti-Chriſtianity of our <hi>Liturgie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> As when one goes forth to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter his Adverſary, with a Ruſh, or Reed onely in his hand, we rationally conclude, that he hath not a Sword, or Spear in his Armory: So, when men bring railing Accuſations onely againſt our <hi>Liturgie,</hi> we may ſafely conclude, That it is becauſe they are deſtitute of every thing, that is ſolid, or ſubſtantial to charge it with. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tatur motu animi, qui uti ratione non poteſt.</hi> We may indulge them the liberty, of their Paſſion, who know not how to make uſe of Reaſon.</p>
            <p n="2">II. Though ſome perſons have (through ignorance or malice) bitterly reproached our <hi>Liturgie,</hi> yet God hath raiſed up others, who have fairly bleſſed, and put a Crown up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the head of it. Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> himſelf hath afforded it ſuch a fair Teſtimony under his Hand, that one would think, his Diſciples (for their Maſter's reputation at leaſt) ſhould for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to blaſpheme it. <hi>Quod ad formulam pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum, &amp; Rituum Eccleſiasticorum, valde probo,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:47534:59"/>ut certa illa extet, a qua Paſtoribus diſcedere in functione ſua non liceat. Tam ut ccnſulatur quorundam ſimplicitati, &amp; imperitiae, quam ut certius ita conſtet omnium inter ſe Eccleſiarum conſenſus. Poſtremo etiam, ut obviam eatur de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultoriae quorundam levitati, qui novationes quasdam affectant.</hi>(Ep. 87. wrote to the Duke of <hi>Somerſet</hi> the Protectour, 22 <hi>Octob. Anno</hi> 1548.)</p>
            <p>Concerning your Form of Prayer, and Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiatical Rites, I do much approve of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Set-Form; from which it ſhall not be lawful for the Paſtours, in their Miniſtration, to recede; as well for their ſakes, who are ignorant, and unlearned; as that the Conſent of the whole Church may thereby the better appear. And laſtly, to prevent the Deſultory Levity of ſome, who affect Novelties.</p>
            <p>Arch-Biſhop <hi>Cranmer,</hi> having Tranſlated King <hi>Edward</hi>'s <hi>Common-Prayer-Book</hi> into <hi>Latine,</hi> ſent it to Mr. <hi>Bucer,</hi> and required his Judgment of it: who anſwered, <hi>That there was nothing in it, but what was taken out of the Word of God: or which was not againſt it</hi> (com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mode exceptum) <hi>being taken in a good ſenſe. There are ſome things indeed</hi> (quae niſi quis, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) <hi>which unleſs they be interpreted with candor, may ſeem not ſo agreeable unto the Word of God, and which unquiet men may wreſt
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:47534:60"/>unto matter of Contention.</hi> Upon which occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that <hi>Book</hi> was ſurveyed; and, in thoſe particulars, ſubject to ſuch Cavils, corrected. I ſhall add onely to theſe two Foreign Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, an equal number of our own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey-men, (both Martyrs.)</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>John Hullyer,</hi> (Fellow of <hi>King</hi>'s <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege</hi> in <hi>Cambridg</hi>) who ſuffered Martyrdom in Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s days, <hi>Anno</hi> 1557.) being at the Stake, among many other Books, that were thrown into the fire to him, it happened, that a <hi>Common-Prayer-Book</hi> fell between his hands, which he joyfully received, open'd, and read, till the flame and ſmoak ſuffered him not to ſee any more: and then he fell to Prayer, holding his hands up to Heaven, and the Book between his Arms, <hi>next his Heart,</hi> thanking God for that mercy in ſending him it (<hi>Acts, &amp; Men.</hi> pag. 18 18.)</p>
            <p>Doctour <hi>Taylor</hi> (in the <hi>Conference</hi> between him, and <hi>Gardiner, Jan.</hi> 22. <hi>Anno</hi> 1555.) <hi>There was</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſet forth by the moſt innocent King</hi> Edward <hi>(for whom God be praiſed ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lastingly) the whole Church-Service, with great deliberation, and Advice of the Learned Men of the Realm, and authorized by the whole Parliament.</hi>
               <q>Which Book was never Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, but once; and yet by that one <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</hi> it was ſo fully perfected, according to
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:47534:60"/>the Rules of our Religion, in every behalf, <hi>That no Chriſtian Conſcience can be offended with any thing therein contained,</hi> 
                  <bibl>(<hi>Acts, &amp; Mon, fol.</hi> 1521.)</bibl>
               </q> Mind the words of this Holy Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr <hi>[No Chriſtian Conſcience can be offended with any thing therein contained)</hi> and yet what Swarms of Exceptions fly in the Face of it? A plenteous ſhowr of Rain, ſeldom brings forth more Muſhroms, (or Toad-Stools) then the late Luxuriant Age hath produced Exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions againſt this Book. Concerning which, take the Judgment of Mr. <hi>Hooker; Whoſoever doth meaſure them by number, muſt needs be out of love with a thing that hath ſo many faults: Whoſoever by weight, cannot chooſe but eſteem very highly of that, wherein the wit of ſo ſcrupulous Adverſaries hath not hitherto ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved any defect, which themſelves can ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly think to be of moment,</hi> (Eccleſ. Pol. B. 5. Sect. 27.) The examination of theſe Exceptions, will be our third Step.</p>
            <p n="3">III. The Exceptions commonly brought againſt our <hi>Liturgie,</hi> are either general, or more particular.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> In general, two things are chiefly laid to its charge.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>It is a Superſtitious Worſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In anſwer to this,</p>
            <p>Firſt, I preſume, <hi>that</hi> (as they ſay Prover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bially)
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:47534:61"/>
               <hi>Every man, that talks of</hi> Robin Hood <hi>never ſhot in his Bow:</hi> So every one, that cryes out <hi>Superſtition,</hi> doth not well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what <hi>Superſtition</hi> is, for <hi>Superſtition</hi> (in the proper, and ſtrict Notion, and ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Word) is the <hi>Worſhip of Idols,</hi> or <hi>Dead Men,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>Superſtites.</hi> Thus St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells the <hi>Athenians, I perceive that in all things you are too ſuperſtitious;</hi> (Act. xvii. 22.) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Thus I ſuppoſe no man hath the Fore-head to charge our <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie</hi> with <hi>Superstition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Superſtition</hi> (in an improper, and more ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally-received Notion) is, when things are either abhor'd, or obſerved, with a zealous, or fearful, but erroneous relation to God: By means of which, the Superſtitious ſerve, either the true God, with needleſs Offices, or defraud Him of Neceſſary Duties, or beſtow ſuch ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and ſervice upon others, as is proper for, and ſhould be peculiar to him onely.</p>
            <p>That our <hi>Liturgie</hi> confers any Honour, or Service, proper, and peculiar to God, upon others, no man hath yet affirmed; That it requires needleſs Offices, to be performed to the true God, no man can ſay, who believes that God (who made oar Bodies, as well as our Souls) requires the external Worſhip of our Bodies, as well as the inward Service of
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:47534:61"/>our Mind. A man cannot expreſs too much in the out-ſide, provided the inviſible part come not ſhort of it; and (I muſt-ſay) I know not how the ſtifneſs of the <hi>Knee,</hi> can be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> from defect of Humility at leaſt, if not of true Piety alſo.</p>
            <p>Secondly, There may be as much Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in rejecting of our <hi>Liturgie,</hi> as in retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it: as much Superſtition, in oppoſing as in aſſerting Ceremonies. A Negative. <hi>Touch not, Taſte not, Kneel not, Bow not,</hi> may be <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious,</hi> as well as the Affirmative. An ignorant fear of diſpleaſing God. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſuch a Form, or Circumſtance of Worſhip, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay, be <hi>Superſtitious</hi> as well, as a <hi>Blind Ze<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> or <hi>Fear</hi> is of all Affections (Anger excepted) the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apteſt to admit any Conference with Reaſon. While a man Superſtitiouſly fears, leſt he ſhould offend, in doing this, or that, he ſins againſt God, and his own Soul, in leaving that undone, which his Reaſon (if he hearken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Voice of it) would tell him he might, and ought to do. This is the firſt, and great, but (you ſee) groundleſs, Exception, againſt our <hi>Liturgie.</hi> The ſecond is like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it; namely, that, <hi>Our Liturgie</hi> is <hi>Popiſh:</hi> or too near <hi>Popery,</hi> being taken out of the <hi>Maſs-Book</hi> To this I anſwer,</p>
            <p>Firſt, (In the words of Learned Mr. <hi>Hocker</hi>)
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:47534:62"/>
               <hi>It were violent, and extream, to ſay, that in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing they may be followed, who are of the Church of</hi> Rome. (They acknowledg the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, of the Old and New Teſtament, to be the Word of God: They make Profeſſion of all the Articles of the Faith; one God, one Saviour, one Baptiſm: it will not (I hope) be deemed <hi>Popery</hi> in Us to do ſo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they do it.) <hi>Some things they do as men, ſome things as wiſe men, ſome things as Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian men; in theſe we may follow them: Some things they do as misled, and blinded with Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour; As far, as they follow Reaſon, and Truth, we fear not to tread the ſame ſteps, in which they have gone, and to be their followers. While</hi> Rome <hi>keeps that, which is antienter, and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, others, whom we much more affect, leaving it for newer, and changing it for worſe, we had rather follow the perfection of them whom we like not, then in their defects reſemble them, whom we love;</hi> (Eccleſ. pol. B. 5. Sect. 28.) <hi>We are ſorry</hi> (ſaith Learned Doctour <hi>Covel</hi>) <hi>that their weakneſs taketh offence at that, which we hold as an honour, and a virtue in the Church of</hi> England; <hi>namely, that we have ſo ſparingly, and as it were unwillingly, diſſented from the Church of</hi> Rome; <hi>with whom, if the Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of that Church would have given us leave, we would have willingly conſented in their whole
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:47534:62"/>Service: which being unſafe, and unlawful, we follow them, notwithſtanding, in all, wherein they follow thoſe Holy and Antient Fathers, which firſt planted the Truth among them.</hi> (Modeſt Exam. <hi>pag.</hi> 185.)</p>
            <p>Secondly, It is no ways probable, were our <hi>Liturgie Popiſh,</hi> that the <hi>Papists</hi> would be ſuch violent Oppoſers of it. We are aſſured by an Argument of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s own making, that it is not <hi>Popiſh:</hi> for (ſaith our <hi>Saviour, Every Kingdom, divided against it ſelf, is brought to deſolation; and an houſe divided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt an houſe falleth;</hi> (Luke. xi. 17.) <hi>John Ould</hi> (in Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s days) wrote againſt the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> in Defence of the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book.</hi> And <hi>Cranmer</hi> made a Challenge, That, if he might be permitted by the Queen, to take to him <hi>P. Martyr,</hi> and four, or five more, they would enter the Liſts with any Papiſts living, and defend the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book,</hi> to be perfectly agreeable to the Word of God, and the ſame, in effect, which had been for fifteen hundred years in the Church of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, It is a known truth, that our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers retained not any part of the <hi>Popiſh Service,</hi> but reformed their <hi>Breviary, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſional,</hi> and <hi>Maſs-Book</hi> (as they did their <hi>Doctrine</hi>) retaining nothing, but what the
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:47534:63"/>Papiſts had received from purer Antiquity: which argues onely a fair compliance in us with the Antient Church, and not at all with them. And if it be ſaid, that ſome Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts have boaſted, that our Service is but their <hi>Maſs</hi> in <hi>Engliſh.</hi> It is (certainly) a moſt unreaſonable thing, that they who will not believe the Papiſt in any thing elſe, ſhould believe them in their vain boaſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, and thinke it an accuſation ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently proved, becauſe ſome Papiſts have impudently ſaid it.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The truth is, the Papiſts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn our Book as much of Schiſm, as the <hi>Conſiſtorian</hi> do of compliance; they accuſe it as much of departing from, the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as the others of remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with it. Now there cannot be a ſurer evidence of the innocency of our <hi>Liturgie,</hi> then the contrary Cenſures, which it hath undergon between theſe two Perſecutours in the extream: it being the dictate of natural Reaſon, that Virtue is infallibly known by this, that is it accuſed by both the Extreams, at guilty of either; as (for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance) the true Liberality of mind is by this exemplifyed, that it is defamed by the Prodigal for Parcimony, and by the Niggard
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:47534:63"/>for Prodigality. Thus you have ſome thing in Reply to the Objections in general, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it appears that our <hi>Liturgie</hi> is neither) Superſtitious, nor Popiſh.</p>
            <p>The particular Objections are excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding many; <hi>but</hi> (as Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> in his Ep. Dedicatory to his fifth <hi>Book:</hi>) <hi>for the greateſt part, ſuch ſilly things, that the eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs renders them hard to be Diſputed of in a ſerious manner.</hi> I ſhall briefly conſider the moſt principal of them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, For the <hi>Litany</hi> (againſt which a Cloud of Darts are caſt) Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> (a Perſon, of whom it is hard to ſay, whether his Sobriety, or Learning may challenge the greateſt admiration) tells us, <hi>that the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute perfection of this piece, upbraids with Errour, or ſomething worſe, them, whom in all points it doth not ſatisfy.</hi> (<hi>Eccleſ. Pol. B.</hi> § 41. (Of the rare effects of which, he gives us (there) two famous Inſtances: the one of <hi>Mamercus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Vienna</hi> (about 450. years after Chriſt) the other of <hi>Sidonius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Averna,</hi> who by the frequent and fervent uſe of the <hi>Rogation,</hi> or <hi>Litany,</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained of God the averſion of portended Calamities, and the removing of Famine, and a Potent Enemy, which beſieg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:47534:64"/>them.</p>
            <p>This part of our Service (<hi>the Litany</hi>) was Called by the Ancients <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, or intenſe Prayer: and in the Greek <hi>Liturgy,</hi> ſimply <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> intenſe, or earneſt. And therefore the Courch requires the Congregation (or, People) to be more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed in it, then in any other part of the Service, Concerning which three things have been offered to be juſtified againſt any Gainſayers; (but no man hath yet en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred the Lifts.)</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>That there is not any where extant a more particular excellent enumeration of all the private, or common wants of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, ſo far as it is likely to come to the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gniſance of a Congregation.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Not a move innocent, blameleſs Form, against which there lies no juſt Objection; and moſt of the unjuſt ones, that have been made, are reproachful to Scripture it ſelf, from which the Paſſages excepted againſt are fetched. As</hi> (for inſtance) <hi>That it may pleaſe thee to have mercy upon all men,</hi> from 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> ii. 1. <hi>I exhort therefore that firſt of all. Supplications, Prayers, Interceſſions, and giving of thanks be made for all men.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Not a more artificial compoſure, for the
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:47534:64"/>raiſing of our zeal, and keeping it up, then this ſo defamed part of our Liturgy.</hi> For which (and other Excellencies, undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it is (and not for any <hi>coniuring</hi> or <hi>ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> in it (as ſome Blaſphemously have ſaid) that the Divel hath took ſuch care, that it ſhould drink de peeſt of the bitter cup of ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnie, and reviling.</p>
            <p>Secondly, For the <hi>Reſponſer,</hi> and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the Presbyter, or Prieſt, in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Sins, and Profeſſion of Faith. They were deſigned by the Church, (from the example of pure Antiquity) to very profitable uſes: as
<list>
                  <item>1. By way of mutual Charity, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple returning a prayer for the Prieſt, who begins one peculiarly for them. <hi>The Lord be with you,</hi> ſaith the Prieſt: <hi>And with thy Spirit,</hi> Anſwer the people</item>
                  <item>2. To quicken devotion which is but to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne to dull and ſlacken by continual heairng.</item>
                  <item>3. To engage every one preſent, to be no idle, or unprofitable ſpectatour, or auditour of the Service onely.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, For the <hi>three Creeds</hi> (the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, Nicene,</hi> and <hi>Athanaſius</hi> his <hi>Creed</hi>) they have been (of old) a badg of the Church, a mark to diſcern Chriſtians, from Infidels, and <hi>Jews.</hi> I have not yet heard
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:47534:65"/>of any thing objected againſt the matter of any of them. The <hi>Apoſtles Creed</hi> (whether delivered by the Apoſtles to the Church by Oral Tradition, that famous Tradition ſo much mentioned by the Fathers: or ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered out of the Writings of the Holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles) is the ſum of the whole Catholick Faith, the Key of the Chriſtian Faith.</p>
            <p>That of the <hi>Councel</hi> of <hi>Nice</hi> was made in that famous Aſſembly of 318. Biſhops, againſt the Hereſie of <hi>Arrius,</hi> who denyed the Coeternity, and Coequality of the Son with the Father</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Athanaſius</hi> his <hi>Creed,</hi> compoſed by that Father. (who alone oppoſed himſelf to that Torrent of <hi>Arrianiſm,</hi> which had over flowed the whole world) was, both in the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> and <hi>Weſtern</hi>-Church, account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as a Treaſure of great price. There is not any imaginable ground of rejecting either of theſe, unleſs is be to gratifie the Separatiſts, who are profeſſed denyers, of one Article <hi>[the Holy Catholick Church.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, For the <hi>Doxology</hi> (or, <hi>Glory be to the Father,</hi> &amp;c.) it is a very antient Piece; the former Verſicle of it, being (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to good Authours) compoſed by the firſt Councel of <hi>Nice:</hi> and appointed by
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:47534:65"/>thoſe Fathers to be uſed in the Church, as a leſſer <hi>Creed,</hi> or Confeſſion of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Conſubstantiality of the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt, with the Father.</hi> At which it hath therefore been the Cuſtom antiently to ſtand up: Confeſſion of God being a praiſing of Him; to which that Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture is moſt due, and proper. And for the other Verſicle [<hi>As it was in the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning,</hi> &amp;c.] when the <hi>Macedonian</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks excepted againſt the Divinity of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> as a Novel Doctrine, Saint <hi>Jerom,</hi> Oppoſition to them, added that unto the former <hi>Verſicle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, For <hi>the reading of the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements</hi> and the <hi>Reſponſes</hi> after them: It muſt be acknowledged, that it is not anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently to be found in the Church, as a part of the <hi>Service,</hi> no not till King <hi>Edward</hi>'s ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>Liturgie,</hi> (by which yet we have this Advantage, <hi>That</hi> Popery <hi>cannot be charged upon it</hi>) yet it will appear to be a profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Part of Devotion. For the Prieſt, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a Prayer for Grace to love God, and keep His Commandements, [<hi>Almighty God, unto whom all Hearts be open,</hi> &amp;c.] is appointed to ſtand, and read the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements diſtinctly to the People: and they
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:47534:66"/>to receive them in an humble Affection of Heart, and convenient Poſture of Body, as means to try, &amp; examine themſelves, to hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble themſelves in a Senſe of their ſeveral Fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, &amp; thereupon to implore, every one for himſelf, and for others (even for the whole Kingdom) Firſt, God's Mercy for Pardon, for every thing, in which we have violated his Holy Commandments [<hi>Lord have Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy upon us</hi>] Secondly, Grace for the time to come, to perform that, which is acceptable to God [<hi>And incline our Hearts to keep this Law.</hi>]</p>
            <p>Laſtly, <hi>For the Communion of the Sick.</hi> It is of long ſtanding in the Church, we have an undeniable Evidence of it, in the <hi>Canons</hi> of the <hi>Councels</hi> about the <hi>Lapſi, &amp; excommunicati,</hi> (the Fallen into ſome ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Sin, and Excommunicate) which take Care, that they ſhould have the Peace of the Church at their Departure out of the World (<hi>in extremis</hi>) and (if with Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of Penitence they, deſire it) the <hi>Holy Sacrament.</hi> No Perſon can be dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatistied with this, who hath, or ſhall, read the famous Story of the dying <hi>Serapion,</hi> in <hi>Euſebius,</hi> lib. 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 36.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:47534:66"/>
And thus there is enough (I ſuppoſe) ſaid, to reconcile any ſober Perſon (who hath a better Eſteem of <hi>Antiquity,</hi> then <hi>Novelty</hi>) to the <hi>Liturgie</hi> of our <hi>Church,</hi> and to confirm thoſe (who are perſwaded, according to Saint <hi>Peter</hi>'s Doctrine) that they ow Obedience to the <hi>Reverend Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops,</hi> as <hi>Governours</hi> ſent by the <hi>King</hi>) in their Religious Obſervation of it, and that ſtrictly, and preciſely, according to the <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick,</hi> in every thing contained in, and required by it at leaſt till the ſame Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, that Eſtabliſhed, &amp; hath ſo often Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed it, ſhall think fit in their great Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms to reform it, I mean, with Soap to waſh, &amp; cleanſe it from any pollutions, that it may poſſibly have contracted, not by <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre,</hi> to tear out the Bowels of it.</p>
            <p>The Inconveniences of altering any thing in the Publick Eſtabliſhed <hi>Liturgy</hi> of a <hi>Church</hi> are ſo viſible and notorious, that no Wiſe men will, without Cogent Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ruſh upon it, becauſe (as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaith from <hi>Socrates,</hi>) <hi>Mutata Muſica, mutantur &amp; Mores:</hi> A Change of <hi>Manners</hi> is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent to a Change of <hi>Muſick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a thing juſtly to be feared, if the Prince ſhall conſent to the taking one, or a
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:47534:67"/>few Bricks out of the Wall, becauſe they are not (as is pretended) well burnt, that the Perſons of that Perſwaſion and Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, will take leave to pluck them out one by one, till they leave no Wall at all. But I hope, the perſons in Authority over us have learned (by a dear bought Experience) to take heed of <hi>Root, and Branch men;</hi> and not to conſent to pull down the whole Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick, becauſe a Window, or Chimney, it may be a Tile onely, is miſplaced.</p>
            <p>It is an unpardonable Errour in any, to think, that the <hi>Act of Reformation,</hi> conſiſts in the taking away things, together with the abuſe of them (if any be) for, that cannot be ſaid to be <hi>Reformed,</hi> which is made <hi>New Reformation</hi> is (properly) <hi>Repetitio vel reſtitutio facti antique,</hi> The Repetition or Reſtitution of an antient Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome. Thus, let our <hi>Liturgie,</hi> (if it ſtand in any need) be <hi>reformed;</hi> but God of his Mercy grant, that neither our <hi>Liturgie,</hi> nor the <hi>Adminiſtratours</hi> of it, fall again under a <hi>Gunpowder-Reformation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is ſaid of <hi>Rome,</hi> that ſhe never un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood what <hi>Cato</hi> was aright, till ſhe had loſt him (<hi>Catonem non intellexit civitas, ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi cum perdidit</hi>) the loſs we ſuſtained
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:47534:67"/>through the aboliſhing our <hi>Liturgie</hi> (by that <hi>Ordinance,</hi> which was diſcharged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it) will have (I hope) ſuch an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion upon the Spirits of all thoſe, that have good will for the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> that it will not (for the time to come) be an eaſy matter for thoſe, that riſe up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, to caſt it down a ſecond time. To prevent which,
<list>
                  <item>1. Do not provoke God through your want of Diligence, in aſſembling your ſelves together, to deliver up the <hi>Liturgie</hi> into the hands of violent men, skilful to deſtroy. If the God of Heaven once perceive (by your negligence in frequenting it) that it is a matter of Indifferencie to you whether you enjoy it, or enjoy it not, he will have a juſt occaſion Adminiſtred, to take that from you, upon which you ſet ſo little va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue.</item>
                  <item>2 Let your Ardour and Fervency in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming this preſcribed <hi>Service</hi> teſtifie to God, Angels, and Men, that your Souls are delighted with it: that it is not the labour of your Lips onely, but the devout breathings of your pious Souls. If you do thus, God will delight to eſtabliſh it, and make it appear, that it is a Plant of your
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:47534:68"/>Heavenly Father's Planting, which no mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal hand ſhall be able to pluck up.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And, if any perſon (to conclude) be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at it, becauſe it is antient, or ſolemn, or ſober or charitable; you may be ſorry for their weakneſs, and labour to inform them: <hi>but be ſure you chooſe rather, to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe one, or a few peeviſh Servants in the Family; then to offend the whole Hous-hold, and incurr the diſpleaſure of the great Maſter of the Houſe, God himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:47534:68"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
